<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A paire of sermons successiuely preacht to a paire of peereles and succeeding princes The former as an ante-funerall to the late Prince Henry, anno Dom. 1612. October 25. The first day of his last and fatall sicknesse. The latter preacht this present yeere 1614. Ianuar. 16. to the now liuing Prince Charles, as a preseruer of his life, and life to his soule.</title>
            <author>Wilkinson, Robert, Dr. in Divinity.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1614</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 109 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15385</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25661</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120035</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855238</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855238</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20719</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15385)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20719)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1563:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A paire of sermons successiuely preacht to a paire of peereles and succeeding princes The former as an ante-funerall to the late Prince Henry, anno Dom. 1612. October 25. The first day of his last and fatall sicknesse. The latter preacht this present yeere 1614. Ianuar. 16. to the now liuing Prince Charles, as a preseruer of his life, and life to his soule.</title>
                  <author>Wilkinson, Robert, Dr. in Divinity.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 89, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Felix Kyngston, for VVilliam Aspley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1614.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Robert Wilkinson.</note>
                  <note>Also issued as part 2 of STC 25664.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20719:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20719:1"/>
            <p>A PAIRE OF SERMONS SVCCESSIVELY PREACHT to a paire of Peereles and ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding PRINCES.</p>
            <p>THE FORMER AS AN ANTE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FVNERALL TO THE LATE PRINCE HENRY, <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1612. October 25. <hi>The firſt day of his last and fatall</hi> ſickneſſe.</p>
            <p>THE LATTER PREACHT THIS preſent yeere 1614. Ianuar. 16. To the now <hi>liuing Prince</hi> CHARLES, <hi>as a preſeruer of</hi> his life, and life to his <hi>Soule.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>DEVT. 30.15.</hi>
               </bibl> Behold I haue ſet before you life and death.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON</hi> Imprinted by FELIX KYNGSTON, for <hi>VVilliam Aſpley.</hi> 1614.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20719:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20719:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCE CHARLES, the happie reuiuing of our former hopes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O you (Most excellent) and to no other ſo properly belongeth the patronage of this fatall payre, whereof the latter was directlie for you, former before you, yea they were both preacht in your hearing, both fitted for your meditation, and now both publiſht at your ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment.</p>
            <p>J confeſſe my ſelfe for late fauours excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly bound vnto your Highneſſe; whereupon bethinking by what meanes J might best either expreſſe or deſerue thankes, me thought a tender of theſe Sermons publiſht might ſerue to doe it, but when J remembred that ſaying, <hi>Doth he thanke that ſeruant, becauſe he did what was commanded him, &amp;c.</hi> J found that J
<pb facs="tcp:20719:3"/>had lost my thankes, becauſe your Highneſſe had ſo commanded it; yea and J find this beſide, that as he who comming to diſcharge his debt, and finding the gold in his purſe to be copper, doth not onely not pay it, but is leſſe able to make payment then before, ſo finde J it with my ſelfe, that either J must ſay with the poore debter in the Gospell, <hi>Haue patience with mee:</hi> or with the woman in the lawe, not able to bring <hi>a Lambe,</hi> J must offer <hi>a paire of Turtles:</hi> And though a paire of Turtles be not a Lambe, nor any action of neceſſarie dutie may goe for testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of thankes, yet J am ſure it may be ſo, if your Highneſſe ſhall ſo esteeme it, for God hath made you a Prince, and Princes are Gods, and it is a part of Gods good nature, <hi>To call things which are not, as if they were.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning the funerall part of this paire, J haue been queſtioned with by others, and haue a little ſtudied in my ſelfe, why in ſuch varietie as the Scripture yeeldeth, J made ſuch a choiſe, as to ſpeake of a <hi>Text</hi> before a liuing, yea a flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing Prince, which the Minister by order rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth before a dead corps: but J haue been better able to make vſe of it ſince, then to giue a reaſon of
<pb facs="tcp:20719:3"/>it before; for now J find, that euen thoſe actions of ours, wherein we leaſt deliberate, yet are dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by God to a ſpeciall purpoſe: and J finde that God had in this an vſe of mee, which J knew not, as the colt caried Chriſt, and yet knew not whether: Jndeed J might well bee questio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with, for bringing <hi>Death</hi> into the Court, which is welcome no where; but leaſt of al there; where though euery day bring forth a new fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion, yet the Mourning garment is ſo out of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion, as <hi>Mordecai</hi> for his garment ſake, <hi>might not come within the Kings gate;</hi> but yet <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> the moſt magnificall of the Kings, and the flower of all Courtiers ſaid, <hi>It is better to goe into the houſe of mourning, &amp;c.</hi> Jnto that houſe doth the former of theſe meditations leade you, there to ſee and conſider, how not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inferiour perſons, but alſo Kings and Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours haue lyen downe in the duſt, and they which haue taxed the whole world haue at laſt paid tribute themſelues, and done their due to nature: Euery man tels you, that what ſoeuer was your Brothers, is now by deuolution yours: giue me leaue alſo to tel you, that as his fortunes, ſo his fate alſo ſhall one day be yours; and that you are
<pb facs="tcp:20719:4"/>not ſo ſure to ſucceede your Fathers in their Thrones, as in their Sepulchres: Jf this pill bee too bitter, the latter part will make amends: for it is <hi>A preſeruatiue to your life,</hi> a receit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt death, and Phyſicke to your ſoule, which if your Highneſſe ſhall receiue, and digest with that mind wherewith it was adminiſtred, it ſhall make you as ſound and immortall, as bee the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and Saints in heauen: And if from my ſtore there hath come any dramme or ſcruple to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that, Oh how happy ſhal I be! yea how happy ſhall J be, to adde but the leaſt drop of life-blood to him, for whoſe life, length of daies, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall happineſſe, ſo many ſoules and aſſemblies of men, yea ſo many kingdomes make dailie ſuite vpon their knees: Then ſhall J ſtyle my ſelfe a new, like Saint <hi>Luke,</hi> an Euangelist and a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician, and ſhall write, not onely, <hi>His Maieſties euer deuoted,</hi> and now of late <hi>more deuinct and obliged Chaplaine,</hi> but alſo</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>One of your Highneſſe Soule-Phyſicians. <hi>Robert Wilkinſon.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:20719:4"/>
            <head>A MEDITATI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON OF MORTALITIE PREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHED TO THE LATE PRINCE HENRY, ſome few daies before <hi>his death.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>IOB. 14.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Man that is borne of a Woman, Short in continuance, And full of trouble.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe words of the Text, though few in number, yet comprehend in a manner halfe the bodie of Diuinitie, for the whole conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting vpon the knowledge of God and man, here is in three words ſo much deliuered concerning man, as threeskore and tenne yeeres, the age of man can expreſſe, <hi>Man borne of a VVoman, Man ſhort in continuance, and Man full of trouble.</hi> So <hi>Man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Totum in toto,</hi> the life of the text, the generall ſubiect of the whole text, and diffuſed into euery
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:20719:5"/>part of it: and indeede what ſhould Man ſtudie ſo much to know as man? He which found fault with Mans creation, for that God had made him two eyes looking out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, but had not made him one eye to looke into himſelfe, hee did lay an vniuſt blame on God, but did iuſtly tax the curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of man: Saint <hi>Austin</hi> ſaith, it is a fault in men, <hi>Eunt homines mirari alt a montium, &amp;c.</hi> Men run out a gadding, or (as we call it) a trauelling, to behold the height and vaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the hils, the immeaſurable bounds and limits of the Seas, the cuſtomes and ſtrange faſhions of all people and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and yet no man truly lookes into him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, like <hi>Salomon</hi> which wrote of Birdes, Beaſts, and Fiſhes, yea of trees and plants, from the Cedar to the Hyſſop, and yet in the meane time fowly forgot himſelfe: It is ſtrange to ſee, what man by his wit hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed for the world, and yet witleſſe to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne what he is himſelfe; in the firſt begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning when the world as yet was naked of inuention, <hi>Jabal</hi> found out a way to herd and bring vp cattell; but no mans policie
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:20719:5"/>yet hath found how to gouerne and order man: and <hi>Jabal</hi> deuiſed by art the muſicall conſent of harpes and organs, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce true vnity from variety; but no man knowes or cares how to accord the iarres and diſcords of reaſon and affection in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: The Artificer by true art hath inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all things, both for neceſſity and for conuenience, which to find, hee hath not left ſo much as the bowels of the earth, or the bottomes of the ſea vnſearcht; but no man yet hath ſearcht or ſeeth ſufficiently into himſelfe; yea looke into the ſchooles, where men ſhould be wiſeft. The Logician rifleth into <hi>matter, forme, efficient,</hi> all the cauſes, yet lackes true Logique to define himſelfe: the Oratour like <hi>Orpheus</hi> makes ſtockes and ſtones to moue, but no man is eloquent enough to perſwade himſelfe to the true obedience and feare of God: The Aſtronomer by art hath gone about, yea and aboue the Sunne, and the Moone; his ſpeculations are tranſcendent to the firſt and higheſt moueable, that if yee will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue him, there is ſcarce a paper wall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:20719:6"/>him and the Angels, he knoweth each ſtarre in his bigneſſe, influence, motion and ecclipſes, yet ſenſeleſſe to vnderſtand the the ecclipſes of his own vnderſtanding, the out-runnings &amp; extrauagancies of his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly affections, the ſhort and flying periods of this fugitiue and tranſitory life. Nay look into the ſchooles of the Diuines, and as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">1. Co. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>we haue all knowledge;</hi> One prieth into, &amp; deſcribeth (as he thinkes) the vnſearchable myſterie of the Trinity, and that with as good warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>r, as the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhemeſh,</hi> when they lookt into the Arke: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother as if hee had peeped in at heauen dores, takes vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him to ſet down the Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchy of heauen, with al the ſeueral orders &amp; offices of the Angels, which he telleth as diſtinctly &amp; ſoberly, as if he knew what he ſaid: another is much troubled about hell fire, as whether it be a materiall torment, or a ſpirituall torment, in which doing (as the diuels ſaid to Chriſt) they <hi>torment themſelues before the time;</hi> and thus we know what God is, and what the Angels are, and we know al things from heauen to hell, and yet wee
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20719:6"/>know not our ſelues, that wee had need of S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſtill to ring in our eares, <hi>Let a man examine himſelfe,</hi> or the text to bee written in great letters before vs, <hi>Man that is borne of a woman, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which text it is generally firſt to bee conſidered, that <hi>Job</hi> ſpeakes not of man, as hee was in Paradiſe, the bright image of God, the commander of ſea and land, the wonder of the world: Not as he was when God firſt made him, the creatures in their kind obeyed him, yea when ſorrow, death and ſickneſſe were afraid to touch him; but <hi>Job</hi> ſpeaks here of man as lapped vp in fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree leaues, hidden among the buſhes, throwne out of Paradiſe, made a ſlaue to miſery and mortality, a ſcandall to the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and a pray to the diuell: Thus in this place doth <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeake of man.</p>
            <p>Againe, it is ſpoken generally, by <hi>man</hi> vnderſtanding all mankinde, euen ſo many as were begot and borne of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue;</hi> It mattereth not for your life, how good or euill you be; it mattereth not for your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, how high or low you be, nor yet for
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:20719:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>your eſtate how rich or poore you be; here is nothing reſpected in man, but onely that he bee <hi>man;</hi> and then let him bee what hee will, euen from the King to the begger, from the Prince to the priſoner, from him that ſits vpon a throne, to him that hanges vpon a tree, yea from the firſt man <hi>Adam,</hi> to the babe laſt borne, all is true of him which heere is ſaid, <hi>Man borne of a woman, &amp;c.</hi> Therefore is any man yet proud of himſelfe? that is, doth any man yet not know himſelfe? then let him come hither, and here he ſhall learne. And here he ſhall learne three points of true humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, the firſt his lamentable, entrance or comming into the world, <hi>Borne of a woman;</hi> the next his ſwift and ſpeedy paſſage out of the world, <hi>ſhort in continuance:</hi> the laſt his wofull pilgrimage and miſerable endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in the world, <hi>full of trouble.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the firſt; it may be ſaid to mankind, as the King ſaid to his euill gueſt, <hi>Quomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do huc intraſti?</hi> How came you in hither, By what meanes or paſſage gat you into the world? you will anſwere out of the text,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:20719:7"/>
               <hi>Natus de muliere,</hi> I was borne of a woman: Well, be it ſo, yet haue you therein confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed two things againſt your ſelfe; firſt that you were borne, and then that you were borne of a woman: Were you borne? <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ore tuo conuincam:</hi> You haue told a tale a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your ſelf; for whatſoeuer was borne, had once a beginning, and whatſoeuer had beginning, there was once a time wherein it had no being in the world; and what were you, or where were you, when you had as yet no being in the world? Here is much adoe amongſt vs about elderſhip and anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, for euery man will be like God:<note place="margin">Dan. 7. Eſa 19. Mat. 3.</note> 
               <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquus dierum: The ancient of daies;</hi> and <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh was the ſonne of ancient Kings:</hi> and the Iewes had <hi>Abraham</hi> to their father, and he is no man now that is not a kin to ſo many Kings, &amp; came not in before the Conqueſt; and hee is much better borne then he; and ſhe is of an elder houſe then ſhe; O vanity of vanities; is not this a meere <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a field picht of frogs and miſe, when vanity hath ſuch place in haroldrie, and we which were borne but yeſterday, yet go to law for
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:20719:8"/>elderſhip? The Iewes had <hi>Abraham,</hi> to their father: <hi>Abraham</hi> was but late and low, they might haue gone farre higher, they might haue fetcht themſelues from <hi>Adam,</hi> if they would; but yet ſtil remembring, that the beaſts of the field, euen horſe and hogs were made before their father <hi>Adam.</hi> And if it ſhould now be asked of one of vs, as ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it was of <hi>Job,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 38.</note> 
               <hi>VVhere wast thou when God laid the foundations of the earth?</hi> Hee would thinke himſelfe mockt, becauſe hee was not borne as yet: Or if hee ſhould bee asked yet lower; Where waſt mould thou when <hi>Noah</hi> and his company were floating in the Arke? Or if yet lower, where waſt thou when God gaue the Law to <hi>Moſes</hi> on the Mount? he would anſwere ſtraight, <hi>Nondum natus,</hi> he was not yet borne: yea examine him yet lower; Where waſt thou, when <hi>Christ</hi> and his twelue Apoſtles walked vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earth? yea aske him but of foure ſcore yeeres ago, or but of threeſcore and ten, and he (alas) was not yet borne; now ſure this is late and young indeed.</p>
            <p>Well, yet at laſt this Mirrour of antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:20719:8"/>is borne; but what hath he to boaſt of by his birth? You will ſay, you were borne; I could anſwere againe, <hi>Poteras &amp; non naſci:</hi> you might haue died vnborne, you might haue died in the birth, or you might haue died ſo ſoone as you were borne: for ſo ſaith <hi>Job</hi> in the pangs of his impatience,<note place="margin">Iob 3.</note> 
               <hi>VVhy hast thou brought me out of the wombe, or wherefore died J not in the birth?</hi> Many are the perils which yet vnborne, and in our birth we paſſe, in which notwithſtanding we are not onely helpleſſe, but alſo ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe of the per ill; this is all we can doe; as hee that hath paſſed ouer a dangerous bridge, turnes backe and quakes to looke vpon the danger; ſo wee when wee looke backe to our birth, and thinke on the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers in it, onely we can ſay with <hi>Dauid, Thou O God</hi> (and not our ſelues) <hi>thou art he that tooke me out of my mothers wombe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 22.</note> 
               <hi>When we are borne,</hi> what then? we fall, (if not hand hold vs) to the feete of her that bare vs, that is, wee fall from the wombe to the ground, from one earth to another; So na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally at the firſt, doe wee finde the way to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:20719:9"/>o r laſt home, euen as God ſaid to <hi>Adam</hi> at the firſt, <hi>Out of earth waſt thou taken, and to earth thou ſhalt returne.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> And oh that wee might ſee, or could we but remember with what pompe and glory wee are borne into the world, Naked as wormes, crawling like ſnakes, that there is not amongſt the creatures ſo weake and helpleſſe a creature as man: the mother (a miſery to thinke) the mother that hath newly borne vs, lieth by vs indeed, but halfe ſlaine by our birth, and leaſt able to helpe vs; ſo we are borne like <hi>Beniamin,</hi> with hazard of her life that gaue vs life, and we ſeeme halfe murtherers ſo ſoone as we are borne; when wee are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vp, what then? we fall a crying, as either repenting of our change, or wiſhing our ſelues vnborne againe; or as if we did fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee the ſequell of the text, the <hi>troubles</hi> which enſue. In the middeſt of this our moaning, wee are, as <hi>Ezechiel</hi> ſpeakes, chap. 16. of his prophecy, we are <hi>waſht, and bathed, and ſwadled in clouts;</hi> No doubt goodly gallants, and great cauſe to bee proud, if wee thought of our ſelues in our
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:20719:9"/>firſt pollution; when wee are thus ſwadle and prankt vp like puppets, a dainty lump of liuing earth: What pleaſure feele wee? nay what feele we? what ſenſe or feeling haue we, ſaue now and then of weakeneſſe and ſickneſſe, the pangs and ſmart of the parents ſinne: We are then brought to the mother, to looke vpon, and ſhe, as a theefe when he is pardoned lookes backe to the gallowes, or to the halter that had like to hangd him, ſo lookes ſhee on her ſon; on her ſonne, as on her death, if God in great mercy had not preuented it: when the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath lookt and kiſt, we are brought to the father too, and to looke vpon too; and while the father looks, euery one cries out, Behold the father, looke vpon the child, ſee ſee, and behold, how like they looke, while indeede they looke more like then they ſhould, and it were well for the child, if it were not ſo father-like, or mother-like as it is: and what get both father and mother by looking, but to looke; as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith of the rich man and his money,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 5.</note> 
               <hi>VVhat good comes to the owners thereof, but the beholding
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:20719:10"/>of it with their eyes?</hi> So looke the carefull parents on a wofull child, ſometime laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with hope of that it may be, ſometime diſtreſſed with feare of that it may bee, watching in the day, wakeing in the night, ſomtime merrie, ſomtime ſorrie, ſometime angrie, that it were not poſſible for them to paſſe through ſo much patience, if God had not infuſed animpregnable affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of loue to ouercome it; thus are we borne in teares and ſorrow to our ſelues, in perill and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row to her that beares vs, in nakednes and ſhame to all that looke vpon vs: here is nothing yet to boaſt on.</p>
            <p>But is our caſe amended, or is our birth magnified by her that bare vs? <hi>Man that is borne,</hi> of what? <hi>of a woman,</hi> as much as to ſay, like neſt, like bird; like mother, like child; but why not as well, <hi>Man begot of a man,</hi> as <hi>Man borne of a woman?</hi> perhaps, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the woman is the weaker veſſell, and the meaning chiefly was, to abaſe man in his owne might; or perhaps becauſe ſinne was firſt inueſted in the woman, and ſince wee ſtand ſo much vpon our antiquity, wee
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:20719:10"/>are only ſinners by antiquity, rebels by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, and rebellion rooted in our firſt blood; ſinners by the father, but firſt by the mother, as by the ſurer ſide; or perhaps it is becauſe ſinne hath more vniuerſally pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed ouer women,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7.</note> for <hi>Salomon counting a thouſand women one by one,</hi> by that account to finde one good one, <hi>found one good man indeed,</hi> but that man was Chriſt, <hi>but not one good woman among them all.</hi> And whether by the woman wee vnderſtand the firſt wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, the mother of mankinde, or elſe the mother of euery ſeuerall man, it comes all to one end,<note place="margin">Iob 25.</note> for <hi>how can hee bee cleane</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bildad</hi>) <hi>which is borne of a woman?</hi> If wee looke to <hi>Eue,</hi> our great grandmother, what haue we to pleade for her? <hi>Adam</hi> was called <hi>Pater viuentium,</hi> the father of al men liuing, and <hi>Abraham</hi> was called <hi>Pater credentium,</hi> the father of the faithfull, or of all the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing, but <hi>Eue</hi> might as well bee called <hi>Mater peccantium,</hi> the mother of all ſinners, and what receiue we by right of ſuch a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but bluſhing at her pride, and feare of her confuſion? If wee looke backe to her
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:20719:11"/>that laſt bare vs, the rocke whereout wee are hewen, oh how little are wee amended by her? for <hi>Jn iniquity was J borne</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid</hi>) <hi>and in ſinne hath my mother conceiued me.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 51.</note> Sinne came from <hi>Eue, A longe,</hi> the date is ſo old, as wee haue forgot how we came by it; but the mother that laſt bare vs, ſhee hath ſtampt it anew with her owne hands, ſhee hath powred it out into vs more natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally then milke out of her paps, yea euen as a poyſon new tapt and freſh out of the vessel; ſo by our grandmother wee haue ſinne tranſlated, and giuen as at the ſecond hand, but by our mother wee haue ſin re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiued and newly incarnate in vs; and haue we not great cauſe then to be proud of her that bare vs: euery man thinkes deepely what good hee hath receiued by his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, what inheritance, what counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, what blood hee hath by them, yea the very name of our anceſtors ſeemeth precious to vs, but yet no man conſidereth that all this is poyſoned with ſinne, and that the whole ſumme of the good doth not counteruaile the leaſt part of the euill
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:20719:11"/>which commeth by them. You will ſay, you were borne of a woman, but what had you by her? you receiued life by her; true, a temporall life, but you receiued withall the reward of ſinne, eternall death; and it were better neuer to be borne, then to bee borne to ſuch a death; you ſucked and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued your foode from her, ſo did you your poiſon too: you receiued your wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, your clothes, and raiment by her; ſo did you your nakedneſſe, your ſhame, and ſinne too: ſumme vp your gettings with your loſſe, and ſee vpon the account what cleerely you haue gained: therefore vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaid the Iewes, wee haue <hi>Abraham</hi> to our father: and idly ſay you, you haue a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, a Counteſſe, or a Lady to your mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: <hi>Sonnes of men</hi> in Scripture are neuer ſpoken of but with reproch, <hi>The ſonnes of men are vanity, the chiefe of men are liers,</hi> Pſal. 62. and <hi>the harts of the ſons of men are fully ſet in them to do euil,</hi> Eccleſ. 8. Thus we glory in our ſhame; yea if we conſider wel, what ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners our parents were, we ſhall be as much aſhamed of them, as <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue</hi> were a
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:20719:12"/>ſhamed of themſelues: wee haue nothing to boaſt of, but the grace of God, <hi>By the grace of God</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>J am that J am,</hi> 1. Cor. 15. though otherwiſe of the tribe of <hi>Beniamin,</hi> an <hi>Hebrew</hi> of the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> &amp;c Though he had <hi>fought with beaſts at Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> and was rapt vp into the third heauens, yet he was nothing of himſelfe, but all by the grace of God: yea as hee that findes a young Serpent, killes it for his very kind, though it haue done yet no harme, ſo may we feare damnation euen by our parents, though wee had done yet no actuall ſinne of our owne, euen as the ſonnes of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <hi>Saul</hi> were hanged for the cruelty of their father vpon the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 21.</note> albeit they were not guilty of it,</p>
            <p>Well, here is our ſickneſſe, that wee are <hi>borne of a woman:</hi> what is the remedy? that we be borne anew by <hi>Christ;</hi> for as the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man with the bloodie iſſue, being ill han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled by her Phyſitians, came vnto <hi>Christ</hi> to be phyſiqued anew, ſo we who be ill borne, and baſe borne at the firſt, muſt come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Christ</hi> to be borne anew. Naturally ſaith
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:20719:12"/>Saint <hi>John,</hi> we are <hi>borne of blood,</hi> ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally therefore wee muſt be <hi>borne of water;</hi> ordinarily wee are <hi>borne of fleſh,</hi> extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily therefore we muſt be <hi>borne of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 3.</note> for <hi>except a man bee borne of water and of the ſpirit, hee cannot enter into the kingdome of God.</hi> Where by <hi>new birth,</hi> wee muſt not groſly fancy a retiring into our mothers wombe againe, as <hi>Nicodemus</hi> did: our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wombe gaue the matter of our firſt impurity, but wee muſt become <hi>new men,</hi> Epheſ. 4. that is, we muſt haue new affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, another ſpirit, a better will, a loathing of the world, and a loue to God; but this wee haue onely by the worke of God, and nothing at all from our mothers wombe.</p>
            <p>After our lamentable entrance &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into the world, the next thing noted, is our ſpeedy paſſage and going out, <hi>Short in continuance,</hi> or as it is originally, <hi>Short in daies:</hi> In which three words foure things are to be conſidered; firſt that the daies of our life are ſhort: ſecondly how they come to bee ſo ſhort: thirdly, how being ſhort, yet they ſeeme by errour to bee ſo long; and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:20719:13"/>fourthly what vſe is to bee made of the ſhortneſſe of our daies. The <hi>life</hi> of man is ſhort, whether by the life of man we mean he life of nature, the age of euery particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar man, or whether wee meane the life of fame, that life whereby wee liue, euen when wee are dead; or whether elſe wee meane the life of all mankind, which is the age of the world: If wee ſpeake of the life of nature, it is not here meaſured out vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs by yeeres, nor by monethes, nor yet by weekes or Sabbaths, but onely by daies, <hi>Short in daies:</hi> leſt with the rich man <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. wee take our meaſure too long, and make account to liue out many yeeres, when the reckoning is, <hi>Hac nocte,</hi> no longer to liue, but to make an end at night. Euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can tell, how many moneths go to a yeere, how many weekes to a moneth, and how many daies to a weeke, but no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> knoweth iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, how few or how many be the <hi>dates of his life; My daies are but a ſpan</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid</hi>) yea my daies are nothing in reſpect of thee:<note place="margin">Pſal. 39.</note> yet let vs go to it by yeeres, and imagine from God a leaſe of the longeſt date, and ſee
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:20719:13"/>how we are deceiued in that;<note place="margin">Pſal. 90.</note> 
               <hi>The time of our life is threeſcore yeeres and ten</hi> (ſaith <hi>Moſes</hi>) or ſet it vpon the tenters, and racke it to <hi>foureſcore,</hi> though not one in euery foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore ariue to that account, yet can we not bee ſaid to liue ſo long: for take out firſt ten yeeres for infancie &amp; childhood, which <hi>Salomon</hi> calles the time of wantoneſſe and <hi>vanity,</hi> Eccleſ. 11. wherin we ſcarce remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber what wee did, or whether wee liued or no, and how ſhort is it then? Take out of the remainder a third part for ſleepe, ſhort <hi>in daies,</hi> ſaith <hi>Job,</hi> hee ſpeakes not of the night, the time of ſleepe, wherein not like beaſts, but like blocks, wee lie ſenſeleſſe, if not liueleſſe, and how ſhort is it then? Take out yet beſides the time of our carking and worldly care, wherein we ſeeme both dead and buried in the affaires of the world, and how ſhort is it then? And take out yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, which muſt not haue the leaſt allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, our times of wilfull ſinning and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, for while we ſinne, we liue not, but we are <hi>dead in ſinne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.</note> and what remaineth of that? yea how ſhort is it then? ſo ſhort is
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:20719:14"/>that life which nature allowes, and yet wee ſleepe away part, and play away part, and the cares of the world haue a great part, and ſinne the greateſt part, that the true ſpirituall, and Chriſtian life hath a thing of nothing in the end.</p>
            <p>If we ſpeake of the life of fame, the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriall life, whereby euen dead men are ſaid to liue, fame hath her wings, not onely to flie about the world, but ſuddenly to va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh and fly cleane away: for how many haue there been of wonderfull note in their times, yet now not remembred ſo much as by name? that no man now can ſay, heere was their trace, here haue they trod, or ſet a foot. Where are they now that led the world in a ſtring, they at whoſe becke both men and beaſts, both ſea &amp; land did bow? they that ſubdued kingdome after king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and ſet one crowne vpon another: they that pitcht vp their Pyramyds and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages of fame vpon the earth, and ſet vp for perpetuall memory their brazen pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers in the ſea: they who while they liued were adored as God, and thought when
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:20719:14"/>they were dead, to bee Calendred among the Gods, yet time and enuie hath eaten out their very names, and where are they now? This is it we call eternall, and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuing honour, yet how ſoone doth it die, and we are gone: nay let worldly fame go, and let vs bee ſought but in the mouthes and thoughts of our beſt, and deareſt ſeeming friendes, and (good God) how ſoone are we forgotten, when we are once gone, that euen they who ſeemed while we liued to loue and honour vs, yet now haue buried their loue with our bodies: while you liue, oh how wiſe, how worthy, how wonderfull are you! yea it is your match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe wiſedome, your incomparable valour, your equitie, piety, and Princely Maieſtie, your excellence and immortall honour; but when the Lion once is dead, then euery Hare dare dance vpon his carkaſe, and dogs dare barke, and Poets then dare raile and rime with pen and tongue, and then this immortall honour dies, and is as mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall as your ſelues.</p>
            <p>But come we to the life of mankind, the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:20719:15"/>age of the world: Indeed of all the reſt, that may ſeeme the longeſt; but as to the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt day at laſt comes night, ſo is the world bounded within the termes of <hi>Creation</hi> and <hi>diſſolution;</hi> it had a beginning, though wee began not with it, and it ſhall haue an end, though wee liue not to ſee it; and all time is ſhort, when it commeth to his end. Wee are borne into the world, as ſome come to a play, yea rather as many come to a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, which came not to the beginning, and happily ſtayed not the end, yet had it both beginning and end, and ſo hath the world to vs: yea the world it ſelfe is but <hi>A ſea of glaſſe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reuel. 4.</note> and glaſſe is no mettall of long endurance; but a time ſhall come, when the Almighty ſhal but blow vpon it, and it ſhal breake in pieces and as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, it ſelfe and all therin ſhall be conſumed with fire 2. Pet.</p>
            <p>Now if any man aske the cauſes of this ſhort life, ſure it is that life and death are in the hands of God, and haue their date and deſtinie ſet by him, yet inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally this vanity and ſhortneſſe of our daies
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:20719:15"/>proceedeth from our ſelues, our life being not onely ſhort in nature, but alſo ſhorten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by our ſelues. Indeed wee are not made of the laſting mettals, there is found in our mixture no ingredience of iron, braſſe, or ſteele, but wee are made of fleſh, which is as graſſe, and all the glory of it as the flower of graſſe; ſo ſoone it fades, and wee are gone: but as if nature of it ſelfe were not fraile enough, wee poſt on to death by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order of our life; for ſometime wrath and enuie fret &amp; gnawes vs, that while we ſeek to kill other men, we kill our ſelues: ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time drunkenneſſe and gluttony conſume and deuoure vs body and goods, yea our very meats eate vp our ſtrength, as we our ſelues eate vp our meates; and ſometime incontinence and fleſhly luſts doe waſt and rot the bodies of men, that as <hi>Martha</hi> ſaid of <hi>Lazarus, Lord hee ſtinkes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>for hee hath been foure daies dead:</hi> ſo it may bee ſaid of ſome, that they ſtinke and putrifie halfe their daies, &amp; yet they liue not halfe their daies: And thus as Babylon made her ſelfe a leaſe of eternity, <hi>A Lady ſure for euer,</hi> Eſa. 47.7.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:20719:16"/>and did eate and drinke in the cups of the Temple, and with her concubines, euen to the night of their deſtruction, Dan. 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.30. So doe we glory in vanity, and triumph in intemperance, and do not only ſuffer mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, but alſo haſten it vpon vs by our ſinne.</p>
            <p>Now, for the cauſes of this error: How comes it to paſſe, that our daies being ſo ſhort and ſo few, yet they ſeeme to vs to be ſo many? much like to him who ſtanding in his gallery, takes a perſpectiue glaſſe, and looketh down into his garden, &amp; there ſees alleyes and walkes, which ſeeme ſo many miles in length, as they are ſcarce diſcerned at their length, and yet when hee comes downe to walke, thoſe many ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing miles make but ſhort turnes, and are meaſured by a few paces. Sure the cauſes of this errour in the computation of our life are chiefly two: firſt for that wee neuer thinke how the time goes, till wee ſee it bee gone; but as the Sunne, though it mooue moſt ſwiftly, yet becauſe we ſee not how it moues, it ſeemeth to ſtand ſtill; ſo our daies
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:20719:16"/>though they paſſe away ſpeedilie, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wee marke them not in the paſſage, they ſeeme to continue ſtill: therfore hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie is that man which euery night can ſay to himſelfe, A day is gone, a part is cut off, ſo much leſſe haue I left of a ſhort and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable life; wee are in the world as Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants in a ſhip, who whether they ſtand, or ſit, or lie, or ſleepe, yet are carried on by the motion of the ſhip; ſo we, whether we eate or drinke, or wake or ſleepe, yet grow on in age and wax old before wee bee aware, and when our time is once gone, then eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie man can ſay to himſelfe, oh how ſhort is this life, how ſoone is it gone? and then it is all one to him who hath liued out his ful foureſcore, as to him who hath liued but foureteene; onely this is the oddes, as Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> ſaith, <hi>Quod ſenior peccatis onuſtior decedat,</hi> That the elder man, and the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger liuer hath ſtill more ſinnes to anſwere to God. The other cauſe of this errour is, for that men conſider the time onely in it ſelfe, and not compared with eternity, which the diuell himſelfe is not ſo fooliſh
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:20719:17"/>to doe, for the diuell knoweth ſaith Saint <hi>John, that hee hath but a ſhort time,</hi> Reuel. 12.12. A ſtrange point of wiſedome in the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, and of follie in vs: ſixteene hundred yeeres agoe, the diuell thought that hee had but a ſhort time, and we thinke a leaſe of three liues to bee a matter of eternitie. Now what is the reaſon of this? becauſe we thinke of no other life, then that which is preſent, whereas the diuell hath an eye to the world to come, the life that ſhall be, in reſpect whereof a thouſand yeers is as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, yea what is ten thouſand to eternity? <hi>The world paſſeth away</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>John, and the luſts thereof,</hi> 1. Iohn 2.17. The world it ſelfe paſſeth, the very frame of heauen and earth ſhall turne to vanity, and therefore the <hi>luſt of it,</hi> that is, whatſoeuer is deſired, admired, or loued in it, ſhall paſſe away with it, and happie is hee that hath not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſht in theſe vaine deſires.</p>
            <p>Now as the perfection of wiſedome is to draw good out of euill, ſo ſhall we come at laſt to be immortall, if we can make true vſe of our mortality. We ſee heere a ſhort
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:20719:17"/>time limited, and yet wee haue a long way to go, euen as far as it is from earth to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and had wee not then need to pray, to haue our life in ſome meaſure prolonged? It is an old and a true ſaying, <hi>Vita breuis, ars longa:</hi> wee haue a ſhort time to liue, and a long Art to learne, euen the Art of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and a few daies wherein to learne it. The baſeſt Art hath full ſeuen yeeres, the tithe or tenth part of our life allowed to learne it, wherein the Maſter takes great paines to teach, the Apprentice takes great pains to learne, and yet happily after much instructing, often beating, early riſing, and late downe lying, he proues a <hi>Non profici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent</hi> too; and are not we aſhamed to thinke that where ſeuen yeeres are deuoted to a mechanicall craft or trade, we of all our life time put together, can ſcarce account of ſo many daies to learne Repentance, which is of ſuch neceſſity, of ſo much difficulty and ſo much better? or doe wee thinke repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to bee but the worke of an houre, faith but a fancy, and all religion to bee of no art or labour? euen <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe who
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:20719:18"/>ſo many yeeres had laboured himſelfe to God, yet complaines and cries out, as if hee had done nothing, <hi>VVretched man that I am, who ſhall deliuer mee from this body of death?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 7.</note> and yet we who haue done nothing, make our ſelues ſecure againſt ſinne and <hi>Satan,</hi> as if one houre were enough to conquer all: vnto this had the righteous reſpect, when they complained of the ſhortneſſe of their liues, and prayed to haue their daies pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed, not for that they feared to die, or loued this fraile life for it ſelfe, wherin they ſaw nothing but miſery and vanity, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they feared leſt death ſhould preuent them before they were prepared, as think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all their daies too few, to learne repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in perfection. Vnto this had S. <hi>Paul</hi> reſpect, when he exhorted the <hi>Corinthians</hi> not to drowne themſelues too deepe in the affaires of this life; this I ſay, <hi>becauſe the time is ſhort</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.</note> 
               <hi>that they which haue wiues be as if they had none, and they which buy as if they poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed not, and they which vſe the world, as if they vſed it not,</hi> and all this he exhorted, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the time is ſhort.</hi> It is a wonder to ſee,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:20719:18"/>how men plant and build, and buy and ſell, as if there were no other life but heere. It is fearfull to conſider how prodigall men are of the time, and loſe theſe golden daies, which they ought to redeeme, while in the meane time heauen flies away, and hell ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtens on them. <hi>Sed ſicut capillus de capite, ſic nec momentum peribit de tempore,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi> God is ſo mercifull to vs, as to keep vs to a haire of our heads, hee ſhall alſo bee ſo iuſt with vs, as to preſſe our account to a moment of time, miſimployed by vs.</p>
            <p>The laſt point generall of the text is our miſerable pilgrimage and endurance in the world, we come in poorely, we goe out quickly, and while we continue, wee conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue carefully: it is not ſhort and ſweet, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther only ſhort and ſwift, but it is ſhort and ſharpe: <hi>Full of trouble.</hi> Some tranſlate and carie it thus, <hi>Satur ira,</hi> Man ſhort in daies, <hi>full of wrath or anger,</hi> which may be ment ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther paſſiuely, by reaſon of the wrath of God vpon vs for our ſinnes: for as it is Pſal. 90. <hi>VVee are conſumed by thine anger, and by thy wrath we are troubled:</hi> and what are all
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:20719:19"/>the plagues of this life, but the execution of Gods wrath vpon vs for our ſinnes? or or elſe it may bee vnderſtood more actiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by reaſon of the <hi>troubles</hi> which man him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, being a turbulent creature, moueth in the world, for wee rage at God himſelfe, when he doth but a little puniſh vs, wee are ſtill at warres and at law one with another, and as <hi>Balaams</hi> Aſſe could tell, the verie beaſts are not free from our madneſſe and crueltie; and therefore <hi>Tremellius</hi> tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it, <hi>Satur commotione,</hi> Man borne of a woman, ſhort in daies, and <hi>full of commotion,</hi> as if all mankind were in a tumult and vp in armes: and ſo wee are indeed, at warres with God,<note place="margin">Eſa. 9.</note> and at warres with one another, <hi>Ephraim againſt Manaſſes, and Manaſſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Ephraim, and both against Judah.</hi> Wee are not quiet in the wombe, but as <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> wee ſpurne and kicke at one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: we are not borne into the world, but with a cry and exclamation, and when wee come into it, we ſtamp and ſtare like Furies on the ſtage, and with the King of Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, wee <hi>make the earth to tremble,</hi> Eſa. 14.16.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:20719:19"/>and if there were no outward thing to trouble vs, yet we haue a pitcht field in our ſelues, ſtill vexed and pained with our owne vnruly paſſions.</p>
            <p>Looke into the ſeuerall ſexes of men and women, and ſee if either of them bee free from trouble. <hi>Jn ſorrow ſhalt thou bring firth, in ſubiection ſhalt thou liue, and thy huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band ſhall rude oner thee,</hi> ſaith God to the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; and then he turneth to the man, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou hast eaten where J forbad thee, Jn ſorrow ſhalt thoa eate thy bread, the earth is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed, thornes and thistles are multiplied, &amp;c.</hi> He muſt labour in wearineſſe, both hee and ſhee muſt die at laſt, and haue their fill of ſorrowes in the meane time; ſhe to ſorrow at home, and in the houſe, hee to ſorrow a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, and in the furrowes of the field; ſhe to ſorrow in bringing forth of children, he to ſorrow in bringing vp of children; ſhee to ſorrow in her ſubiection to him, and hee to ſorrow, yea a great deale of ſorrow, in paſſing his time with her, that leſt they ſhould lacke trouble, they ſhould bee a cauſe of mutual trouble to themſelues, and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:20719:20"/>ſorrow in their very comforts, as <hi>Lot</hi> was plagued in Sodome, which hee choſe out for his pleaſure.</p>
            <p>Againe, is there any time or age free from trouble? ſurely none, for in ſorrow ſhalt thou eate thy bread (ſaith God) <hi>All the dates of thy life,</hi> Gen. 3.17. Begin with child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and can any miſery or trouble bee there? yes ſure, the things which are moſt neceſſary, are miſerable to a child; the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtering and breaking of his will ſeemes op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion to him, but the ſhaking of the rod is flat perſecution: light ſorrowes (you wil ſay) in reſpect of the greater troubles which enſue: It is true, they are ſo; yet a little trouble is great, where there is neither reaſon to conceiue the neceſſity, nor pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence at all to beare it. But then comes on youth, headdy, aduenturous, voluptuous, paſſionate, and prodigall youth, wherein al our actions and courſes, whether good or euill, yet miniſter matter of vexation to vs; For, labour wee? indeed our youth is the time of our labour; yet our very labours ſpend vp our ſtrength, that had wee not a
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:20719:20"/>ſeuenth day to reſt from the ſorrowes of the ſixt, wee ſhould faint and die. Againe, ſtudie wee? an eaſie trade, an idle kind of life: The world ſaith to vs,<note place="margin">Exod. 5.</note> as <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi> to the <hi>Jſraelites, Ye are too much idle;</hi> yet <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaid, that <hi>Much reading was a wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſſe to the fleſh,</hi> Eccleſ. 12. Againe, reſiſt we (as young men ought to doe) our euill luſts and deſires? 1. Ioh. 2.14. Oh how ſweet are the luſts of youth? how ſtrong are the temptations, and what a paine it is to reſiſt the things which are pleaſing to vs? But play wee, or follow wee our pleaſures? in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed that is the naturall trade of youth, as Eccleſ. 11.9. <hi>Reioyce O young man in thy youth, &amp;c.</hi> yet are wee no way more vexed and plagued then by our pleaſures: for as a theefe robbes in feare, and an adulterer (though the dores bee faſt lockt) yet is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid ſtill; ſo is there a checke of conſcience which bites the moſt riotous in the midſt of their riot. Againe, if our pleaſure bee in prodigality, our end muſt be beggery, that ſin being peculiarely a ſcourge to it ſelfe; and many times before the Prodigall can
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:20719:21"/>ſpend vp all, the priſon, the preſſe, or the halter do ſpend vp him, &amp; miſerable is the end of a voluptuous life at laſt; which made <hi>Salomon</hi> to ſay, <hi>J haue ſaid of laughter, thou art mad, and of ioy,</hi> that is, of wanton ioy, Oh what is it that thou doeſt, Eccleſ. 2.</p>
            <p>But liue we to be aged? then liue we to be diſeaſed, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> liue we to be deſpiſed, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> liue we to blindnes, lamenes, deafnes, to pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, aches, agues, all that euer Chriſt came to cure; wee are neuer throughly troubled till then. The fore part of our life had yet ſome ſhew of pleaſure, but theſe are (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) <hi>the euill daies, the dates wherein thou ſhalt ſay, J haue no pleaſure in them.</hi> Eccleſ. 12. Theſe are the daies wherein <hi>Barzillai</hi> eats, and knowes not what he eates; his taſte is gone: theſe are the daies wherein old <hi>Jſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ac</hi> gropes and feeles <hi>who art thou? come neare me, let me feele thee:</hi> his ſight is gone: theſe are the daies wherein <hi>Jacob</hi> halts &amp; limps, and muſt haue a ſtaffe to leane on; his ſtrength is gone; and <hi>Dauid</hi> muſt haue <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhag</hi> to warme his blood, and to cheriſh him, becauſe his naturall heate is gone; ſo
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:20719:21"/>as now wee are not onely miſerable men, but wee are ſcarce men, for wee haue (like images) eyes and ſee not, eares and heare not, wee haue hands and feele not, feet and goe not, and ſcarce make we any ſound in our throates; that it may truly bee ſaid of vs, that in our youth wee ſin, but in age we receiue the puniſhment of our ſin, and the neerer our end, the more is ſtill our trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and miſery.</p>
            <p>But looke againe; Is there any ſtate or condition free from trouble? ſurely none; for is a man poore, God ſend him patience, hee ſhall neuer need to pray for trouble to exerciſe it; hee ſhall haue trouble enough; hunger, cold, and nakedneſſe in his body, and in his mind ſuch diſcontent, as few of that condition haue wiſedome to mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate: hee ſeeth himſelfe forſaken of his friends, ſcorned of his enemies, and negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted of all: he railes on him that giues him not, he grudgeth and enuieth at him which hath to giue him, yea and he is angry euen at God himſelfe, becauſe he did not equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diuide the things of the world. But is
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:20719:22"/>any man rich? rich men haue ſure no trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at all; yes they haue labour and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to get, and care and trouble to keepe, and feare and trouble to loſe; which S. <hi>Gregory</hi> well deſcribes, <hi>Sipotentiorem videt timet raptorem; ſi inferiorem, ſuſpicatur fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem, &amp;c.</hi> If he ſee a mightier man then him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, he thinkes he comes to oppreſſe him; if hee ſpy a poorer man, hee is preſently in doubt that hee comes to ſteale from him; and euery little noiſe is the breaking of his doores, euery mouſe is a man, euery man is a theefe, &amp; euery theefe points at him, <hi>Et tanta patitur infoelix quanta patit timet;</hi> It comes with a feare, hee dreames it, and hee feeles it; beſides, he oft times gets it ſinful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſpendes it ſinfully, and ſometimes keepes it ſinfully, that Chriſt ſaith ſuch men can hardly enter into the kingdome of heauen: beſides, wheras there is almoſt no ſinne, but a man hath ſome pleaſure in the execution of it; for <hi>ſtolen bread</hi> is ſweet to the theefe, and <hi>ſtolen waters</hi> are pleaſant to the adulterer:<note place="margin">Prou. 9.17</note> many rich men are miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble not only in the getting, but euen in the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:20719:22"/>abundance of their riches; for though they haue much, yet they cannot finde in their hearts to vſe it, but as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, they <hi>defraud their ſoules of pleaſure,</hi> Eccleſ. 4.8. for they neither fare daintily, nor are clothed ſoftly, but liue and die and doe all things miſerably, and yet goe to the diuell when they haue done.</p>
            <p>Againe, if a man liue in the ſtate of a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, that ſtate is his trouble; for <hi>if thou maiſt be free</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>vſe it rather,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 20.</note> 1. Cor. 7.21. God in the law did yoake and put cloſe together, <hi>His man ſeruant, and his maid ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, his oxe, and his aſſe:</hi> as if a ſeruant for his ſtripes and labour were next in degree to an oxe and an aſſe; yea and the more faithfull and the better a ſeruant is, the worſe many times hee fares, for euen his vertue, which ſhould bee a crowne of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward vnto him, it proues but a chaine of bondage, more inſeparably to fetter him to his maſter; ſo as that which was firſt but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued in the Court, is now an obſeruation euen in the countrie too, <hi>Fidelis ſeruus per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuus aſinus,</hi> that a faithfull ſeruant is an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:20719:23"/>aſſe. Yea and though a man liue in ſtate of a maſter, yet he hath <hi>Miſeriam in imperio,</hi> he hath command, and authority, and ſoueraignty, and trouble enough too; for if hee be meeke and gentle, familiaritie breeds him contempt, and hee is deſpiſed; but if he be ſtrict and ſeuere, he is hated: and as the maſter enricheth himſelfe by the bondage of his ſeruant; ſo the ſeruant ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time payeth himſelfe with the goods of his maſter.</p>
            <p>But wee haue cleane forgot one thing, and what is that?<note place="margin">2. Sam. 15.</note> 
               <hi>Oh</hi> (ſaith <hi>Abſolon</hi>) <hi>that J were King in the land:</hi> and what of that? why, whereſoeuer a King is, there is peace, and eaſe, and honour, there is no <hi>trouble</hi> there. A King weares a Crowne; a Crowne is ſet with pearles, and pearles are excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding precious: A King hath a Scepter which commands all; and is commanded by none: A King hath a royall Throne, he may ſit when other men ſtand, and if ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting be not eaſe enough, hee may leane, or lie downe to ſleepe, where other wake; he may eate and drinke, and dice and carde,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:20719:23"/>and worſe then all that, and yet when hee hath done his worſt, it is well done, and who dare ſay, why haſt thou done it? Such is the errour of men, to impute leaſt trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble there, where God hath placed moſt. But <hi>is not for Kings O Lemuel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 31.</note> 
               <hi>it is not for Kings to drinke wine, nor for Princes ſtrong drinke,</hi> Yea rather <hi>the vine must leaue his wine, the Oliue his fatneſſe, and the figtree his ſweetneſſe, if they went to aduance themſelues aboue the trees,</hi> Iudg. 9. and why is it, that none of theſe ſaid vnto the trees, Come, make mee king, but the trees went a begging to them and ſaid, <hi>Come and be thou King ouer vs?</hi> but to ſhew that if men reſpected only quietnes and worldly eaſe, a kingdome were not worth the asking. <hi>Valerius</hi> reports of a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then King, who when the Crowne was of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered him, ſtood firſt and lookt vpon it, and talked to it, before hee would accept and take it, <hi>Oh if men knew the miſery that comes with thee, there is no man would stoope to the ground to take thee vp.</hi> For <hi>Ex quo regna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re cepi, nunquam pauere destiti,</hi> ſaith the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicall King, he was euer in feare, &amp; neuer at
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:20719:24"/>reſt, ſince firſt he tooke the regiment vpon him. For when a King lookes vp to God, hee thinkes firſt of the account which hee muſt make to him, becauſe all the ſinnes of the people lie vpon the King, <hi>Rex non modò peccat, ſed &amp; peccare facit,</hi> a King doth not onely ſinne himſelfe, but alſo makes the people to ſin, either by ſufferance, as <hi>Aaron</hi> did, or by example, as <hi>Salomon</hi> did, or by tyrannous compulſion, as <hi>Jeroboam</hi> did, of whom it is ſaid ſeuenteene times in the bookes of the Kings, that <hi>he ſinned and made Jſrael to ſin:</hi> &amp; how then? why then, as when the people firſt began the making of the golden Calfe, yet <hi>Aaron</hi> was firſt called in queſtion about it, Exod. 32.21. <hi>VVhy hast thou brought ſo great a ſinne vpon the people?</hi> ſo Kings &amp; Princes muſt account to God, not onely for their owne ſinnes, but alſo for the ſins of the people: and were there no other trouble then this, yet this very point of accounting to God is a trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and fearefull thing to thinke of.</p>
            <p>Beſides, what art and great labour haue Kings in the very act of gouernment: It is
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:20719:24"/>an art of all arts (ſaith <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi>) to gouerne man, who is ſo wild a beaſt, and vntamed of himſelfe.<note place="margin">Exod. 18.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes</hi> ſat from mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to euening, to heare and determine cauſes, that <hi>Jethro</hi> pitied much to ſee him ſo wearie and ſo tired: and it was truly ſaid of <hi>Maximinus,</hi> one of the Romane Emperours, <hi>Quo maior fuero, eo magis labora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo:</hi> The greater I am the greater labours, I ſee, will ſtil befall and lie vpon me; and the Lion, which is king of the beaſts, is ſaid to ſleepe with his eyes open, to ſhew that it is no ſleepie life to be a king. Beſides, what perturbations of feare are in the mindes of Kings, more then of other men, who may feare euery cup, and euery bit, and euery gift; who feare their enemies, and feare their friends, becauſe they know not their enemies from their friends; for neither the habit, be it neuer ſo religious, nor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour of men, be it neuer ſo humble, can promiſe ſecurity to Princes, witneſſe the laſt but one of France,<note place="margin">Henry <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> ſlaine by a Frier Iacobine, euen crouching and kneeling on his knee: yea, are not Kings more ſubiect
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:20719:25"/>to violent death then the common ſort of men? Of the Kings of <hi>Judah,</hi> from <hi>Reho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam</hi> down to <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> there were in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber twentie, and ſix of them, that is, almoſt a third part ſlaine. Againe, of the Kings of Iſrael, from <hi>Jeroboam</hi> downe to <hi>Oſhea,</hi> there were alſo in number twentie, and tenne of them, that is, a iuſt halfe ſlaine: Yea looke into our owne ſtories, and our Engliſh Chronicles are all bloody; from the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt downeward (which is better known) of three and twentie deceaſed Princes, eight, that is, more then a third part ſlaine, beſides the Tragicall reports of France &amp; other countries. Now ſure it were a moſt fearefull thing amongſt the common ſort of men, if one in euery three were ſubiect to violent death. And whether ſhall a man turne, but the higher, ſtill the more trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome. and more infortunate. Oh therefore value nothing too high which death doth aboliſh: dote not too much on death, and troubles, and golden miſery. Let not men ſet their hearts on that which cannot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit them; or if it pleaſe a little, yet it will not
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:20719:25"/>long ſtand by them. If here wee ſeeke for peace, it wil be anſwered, as the Angels ſaid of Chriſt, <hi>Reſurrexit, non eſt hic.</hi> Indeed it is often promiſed heere, the world &amp; the fleſh make promiſe of it, and wee like falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets cry Peace, peace, and promiſe it to our ſelues, but the true peace is gone vp with Chriſt, and is not here:<note place="margin">Mat. 28.</note> and Saint <hi>John</hi> was commanded to write it for aſſurance, <hi>Write<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from hence forth bleſſed are the dead, for they rest from their labours,</hi> Reuel. 14.13. they reſt <hi>hence forth,</hi> but they reſt not here; and therefore ſince wee haue no reſt, but ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, and warres, and troubles here, let vs not ſeeke our reſt here, leſt if we ſpend our time in ſeeking where it is not, wee faile to finde it where it is. God of his mercy draw our mindes from the deceit of this vaine, miſerable, and ſinfull world, and lift vp both our hearts vnto the hope, and our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauours vnto the purſuit of eternity, euen for Ieſus Chriſt his ſake: To whom with the father, &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:20719:26"/>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:20719:26"/>
            <head>THE KINGS HIGH WAY TO IM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie.</head>
            <head type="sub">A SERMON PREACHED this preſent yeere, <hi>Ann. Do.</hi> 1614. Ian. 16.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTY</hi> Prince CHARLES, at his houſe and Chapell of S. <hi>Iames.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PRO. 4.3.4.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <lg n="3">
                     <l>For I was my fathers ſonne,</l>
                     <l>Tender and deare in the ſight of my mother.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="4">
                     <l>When he taught me, and ſaid vnto me,</l>
                     <l>Let thy heart hold faſt my words,</l>
                     <l>Keepe my Commandements, and liue.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſt renowned and excellent; But that ſorrowes make ſhort times ſeeme long, it is not long, ſince at vnawares, and not knowing what I did, I made vnto your deceaſed and now immortall brother a Sermon of Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:20719:27"/>or of death: It is now fallen out by Gods prouidence, and which (God himſelfe being witneſſe) I did not thinke of, when I choſe the text, that I muſt make vnto your Highneſſe a Sermon of life: but as I had then no ſpecial illumination or prophecy, that death was ſo neare to him, ſo haue I now no abſolute promiſe of life to you, but vpon the conditions heere annexed, <hi>Let thy heart hold fast my words, Keepe my Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, and thou ſhalt lieu,</hi> which are the words of <hi>Dauid,</hi> the ſpeech of a King, and therefore of weight and moment; and it is a ſpeech made to <hi>Salomon,</hi> the ſonne of a King, and therefore pertinent; and it is a ſpeech taken from the mouth of the King the father, by the pen of the King his ſonne, and therefore not loſt, or let fall to the ground, (as good counſell oft times is) but recorded as a thing for euer permanent. And wee may diſtinguiſh in it two things, which diuide it into two parts; for firſt <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> ſheweth, what tender loue his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents bare vnto him, <hi>He was his fathers ſon, Tender and deare in the ſight of his mother,</hi> and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:20719:27"/>then hee ſheweth next by what teſtimonie they expreſſed their loue vnto him, <hi>They taught him and ſaid vnto him, Let thy heart hold fast, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the firſt, that <hi>Salomon</hi> was to his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thus, and to his mother thus and thus, it is a tale vndoubtedly true; but how a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth it with <hi>Salomons</hi> wiſedome to tell it? They ſay, a chiefe point of wiſedome is to keepe counſell, eſpecialiy to conceale the ſecrets of a King, but moſt eſpecially to keepe ſecret what Kings and Queenes doe in their chambers, and among their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. It may bee that <hi>Dauid</hi> loued <hi>Salomon</hi> exceeding much, how then? It may be like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe that his mother loued him exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly more; and what of that? perhaps when he was ſwadled in clouts, and lapt vp in a mantle, ſhee might take him in her armes, and talke like a mother to him; perhaps when he was able to goe vpon his feet, yet ſhee might ſet him on her knee and dance him, yea and it may bee too, that when hee was able to dance and leape about him ſelf, yet ſhee, as her owne pretty, apt, and actiue
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:20719:28"/>child, might take him to her, and kiſſe him; and what of all this? was there no other way, but to take a pen and write a booke of theſe things? To which I anſwere with the Apoſtle generally, <hi>that whatſoeuer things are written, they are written for our instructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> Rom. 15.4. And that as the things which the holy Ghoſt hath concealed, are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not fit to bee knowne; ſo the moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret things (as the drunkenneſſe, yea the nakedneſſe of <hi>Noah</hi>) when they any way make for publike edification, they are iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly publiſht, and needfully made knowne.</p>
            <p>The occaſion of this report, I take to be thus: <hi>Salomon</hi> would perſwade children, or young men to learne, what is the true wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome or vnderſtanding; for ſo it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares, verſ. 1. of the chapter: <hi>Heare O yee children the instruction of a father, and giue eare to learne vnderstanding.</hi> And to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade that, hee brings in himſelfe for an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, <hi>For J was my fathers ſonne, &amp;c.</hi> As much as to ſay, Thus was I taught, thus did I learne when I was a child; the tendernes of my yeers did not excuſe me, neither the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:20719:28"/>loue of my parents, nor yet my royal birth did priuiledge me to neglect theſe things; therefore <hi>Heare ye children alſo, and giue eare to learne vnderstanding:</hi> That other mens children ſhould learne by example of the Kings: the conſequence is very reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: If the Kings ſonne did learne and ſtudy theſe things, then much more the ſonnes of meaner men; but the <hi>Antecedent,</hi> that the Kings ſonne did learne theſe things, it is the very point of the text, and it is a point of Princely conſideration. The ſtrength of the reaſon lieth in <hi>Salomons</hi> own perſon, <hi>For J was; Heare ye, and learne ye, For J was</hi> thus, and yet learned thus. <hi>Salomon</hi> heere ſpeaketh like a King, and teacheth Kings likewiſe how to ſpeake: that is, if they will perſwade the people any thing, to ſhew the experience of it firſt in themſelues; or if they will command the people any thing, to ſhew the ſame thing firſt done by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, <hi>For J was thus,</hi> and yet learned thus, that is to ſay, hee layeth no other burthen on the people, then he had firſt borne him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. Kings and Prieſts in a common
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:20719:29"/>ſenſe are both ſaid to bee ſhepheards, but <hi>the good ſhepheard goeth before</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>and then the ſheepe follow after,</hi> Iohn 10. It is ſaid in the praiſe of <hi>Moſes,</hi> that <hi>hee was a man mighty both in word and deed,</hi> Acts 7. Mighty in word, as many gouernours are, to command ſtrongly, but mighty alſo in deed to doe it accordingly. <hi>Tully</hi> reports of <hi>Julius Caeſar,</hi> that hee was neuer heard ſaying to his ſouldiers, <hi>Jteilluc,</hi> Goe ye thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as if they ſhould go forth vpon ſeruice and he to tarrie behinde in his tent, but <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite huc,</hi> Come ye hither, as if hee had ſaid, Come on my hearts, let vs giue the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture, and aduenture our ſelues toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for <hi>Participatus cum duce labor perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>detur militibus minor,</hi> it ſhall bee an eaſie thing for the common ſouldiers to follow, when they ſee the Captaine goe before; but if a Magiſtrate ſhall exact of the people one thing, and doe himſelfe another, they will ſay he is like a water-man which rowes one way, and lookes another. <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>Macedon</hi> was very curious and inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue about the agreement of the <hi>Grecians</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:20719:29"/>themſelues, and yet liuing in an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible diuiſion with his owne wife: ſuch a man, though neuer ſo high, yet is lookt at, like one vpon a ſtage; yea how can a King or Magiſtrate puniſh ſin in another man, when he is noted to be guiltie, yea and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious in the ſame ſinne himſelfe? <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> the great conqueror tooke one <hi>Dyoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des</hi> a Pyrate vpon the ſea, and asked of him, <hi>Quid ſibi videretur, vt mare infestum fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceret,</hi> what hee meant in that manner to trouble the ſea? the Pyrate anſweres him boldly and truly againe, yea rather, what meane you thus to trouble the whole world? but becauſe I robbe and ſteale in a poore pinnace, which you doe in a great and royall Nauie, I goe for a Pyrate, and you goe for an Emperour: and when it is thus with the Magiſtrates in a kingdome, though no man dare ſpeake, yet euery man will mutter, and <hi>Socrates</hi> will laugh, <hi>Quia video magnes latrones ducentes paruum latro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ad ſuſpendium,</hi> becauſe he ſaw the great theeues leading the little theeues to hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. And ſo much for the perſonall point,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:20719:30"/>
               <hi>For J was.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well, what was he? <hi>J was my fathers ſon, Tender and deare in the ſight of my mother:</hi> that is to ſay, he was his fathers, and he was his mothers, begotten of the one, and born of the other; and as the male and female of the doues doe hatch and feede their young by courſe, euen ſo was hee diuided to them both. But firſt, <hi>Altera pars patri,</hi> one peece goes to the father; <hi>He was his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſonne:</hi> his fathers ſonne? that muſt needs bee true in reaſon, and yet it ſeemes triuial to write, for euery child in Logique knowes the Relatiue predication, <hi>Filius est patris filius,</hi> and how can a man but bee his fathers ſonne? yet the Scripture vſeth this phraſe of ſpeech, either when the child doth much reſemble the father, as Ezech. 16. <hi>Thou art thy mothers daughter,</hi> that is, like mother, like daughter, an ill whelpe of an ill ſtore; and in that ſenſe Chriſt denieth the lewes to be the ſonnes, becauſe <hi>they did not the workes of Abraham,</hi> Ioh . 8.39. Or elſe the ſonne is ſaid to be the fathers, when he is ſo reſpected, and ſo accounted of the father,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:20719:30"/>and that is the meaning or <hi>Salomon</hi> heere, <hi>J was my fathers ſonne,</hi> that is, my father be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat me, and owned me, and loued mee, and ſaw himſelf in me. It is ſaid of the Oſtrich, that <hi>ſhee is cruell to her young, as if the were not hers,</hi> Iob 39. Such an Oſtrich was <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liah,</hi> 2. King. 11. that catcht vp her grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>children, and killed them as ſhee catcht them, as if they had not been the ſonnes of her ſonne. And <hi>Augustus Caeſar</hi> ſaid of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod,</hi> that hee had rather bee <hi>Herods</hi> ſwine, then his ſon, for that being in part a lew, hee forbare to kill ſwine, and yet vpon a bare conceit hee killed two of his owne ſonnes: But <hi>Salomon</hi> was <hi>his fathers ſonne,</hi> and <hi>Dauid</hi> was to <hi>Salomon</hi> a kinde and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing father, &amp; yet not taxed heere with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence neither; nor doe we any where teach, that naturall loue is a ſinne, or that religion doth forbid it, but only bridle and gouerne it: yea it came firſt from the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and with a voice from heauen, for the father to loue his ſonne, <hi>This is my belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſonne,</hi> ſaith God the father of Chriſt his ſonne, Mat. 3. And the beſt men were thus
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:20719:31"/>affected to their ſons. Take now thy ſon, <hi>thy ſonne whom thou louest,</hi> ſaith God to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> Gen. 22. And ſo were the worſt men affected to their ſons, for euen they <hi>which were euill, yet gaue good gifts vnto their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> Mat. 7. Yea the cruell beaſts doe loue their own, <hi>The Dragons draw out their breaſts and giue ſucke to their young,</hi> Lament. 4. and 2. Tim. 3. It is reckoned for one of the ſigns of the latter day, that men ſhall bee <hi>without naturall affection.</hi> Now the reaſon why men do naturally loue their children, is not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they bee wittie, or faire, or forward, (though theſe things may encreaſe their loue) but becauſe they be theirs. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why good men loue their children is, not onely becauſe they bee theirs, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe (as they thinke) they bee heires be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten vnto God. But the reaſons why Kings doe loue their children are many more, and more peculiar. Firſt becauſe they ſee all the people loue them, which <hi>Saul</hi> ſaw in <hi>Jonathan,</hi> when they reskewed him out of his fathers hands, and deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him from death, 1. Sam. 14. Secondly,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:20719:31"/>becauſe the royall ſeed and name is preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in them, which was promiſed to <hi>Dauid</hi> in this <hi>Salomon,</hi> 2. Sam. 7. Thirdly, becauſe Kings of all men being ſubiect to plots and practiſes while they liue, and alſo to ill fame and cenſure when they are gone: their ſons ſtand vp, not only as heires to inherit their crownes and kingdomes, but as Champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to maintaine their honours, and to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge their quarrels, whereof the former was performed by <hi>Jotham</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deon:</hi> Iudg. 9.17. The latter by <hi>Amaziah</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Joaſh,</hi> 2. King. 14.5. Fourthly, the King loueth his ſonne the more for a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine myſterie hi him; for as Kings them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues are Gods, ſo is the ſonne of the King as the ſonne of God: God ruleth he world by Chriſt his ſonne. Iohn 3.35. So did <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> yet liuing ſet <hi>Salomon</hi> vpon his owne Mule, yea vpon his owne Throne, 1. Kin. 1. God pronounceth his ſonne the <hi>onely medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator</hi> to himſelfe, 1. Tim. 2.5. He in whom he <hi>is well pleaſed,</hi> Matth. 3.17. So did <hi>Dauid</hi> worke himſelfe peace with <hi>Saul</hi> a while, by the mediation of <hi>Jonathan</hi> his ſon. 1. Sam.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:20719:32"/>19. 6. and as the ſonne of God is the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the father, 1. Cor. 1.24. So ſaith <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> heere, that his <hi>father taught him,</hi> that is, put wiſedome to him, and he did not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly teach him, but alſo prayed for him in that behalfe, <hi>Giue thy iudgements to the king, O God, and thy righteouſneſſe to the kings ſon,</hi> Pſalm. 72. and thus was <hi>Salomon his fathers ſonne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to his mother, what? <hi>Tender and deare,</hi> or as ſome tranſlate it, <hi>Tender and on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the ſight of his mother.</hi> To his father a <hi>ſonne,</hi> barely and without addition, His <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſonne,</hi> but to his mother her <hi>tender ſon,</hi> her <hi>deare,</hi> her <hi>onely ſonne:</hi> So the father ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth downe the Subſtantiue, but <hi>Tender and onely,</hi> the Adiectiues or Epithetes come from the mother: and why ſo? becauſe <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> ſhould ſhew that his father loued him, but his mother loued him more; euen as commonly wee ſay, that men abound in reaſon, but women in affection: <hi>Thy loue to me was wonderfull, paſſing the loue of women:</hi> ſaid <hi>Dauid</hi> to <hi>Jonathan,</hi> 2. Sam. 1. A won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull loue, (no doubt) which paſſeth the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:20719:32"/>loue of women. Or elſe <hi>Salomon</hi> would ſhew, that his fathers loue was in diſcretion hid, as in the text it is but vnderſtood; but his mothers loue was <hi>Tender,</hi> and <hi>deare,</hi> and <hi>onely,</hi> flaming out like fire, which hath no power to hide it ſelfe: for <hi>Can a mother for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get her child</hi> (ſaith <hi>Eſay</hi>) yea can a mother hide her affection from her child? yes, iuſt as <hi>Salomons</hi> mother hideth hers; <hi>VVhat my ſonne, and what the ſon of my wombe, and what O ſonne of my deſires,</hi> Prou. 31. See, how ſhee hides her loue, <hi>Her ſonne,</hi> and <hi>the ſonne of her wombe, and the ſonne of her deſires,</hi> as if ſhee had ſaid, O thou my ſonne, whom once I bare in my wombe, and whom I euer beare in my heart, borne of my body by courſe of nature, but ſtill vnborne by ſtrength of loue, the father ſaith, <hi>Sonne, thou art euer with me,</hi> Luk. 15. The mother ſaith Sonne, thou art euer within me; and ſo is it heere, <hi>Tender and onely in the ſight of his mother. Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> in reſpect of his age, as Chron. 1.29. <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomen my ſonne, young and tender,</hi> but more in reſpect of her affection, as mothers are euer tender, that is, fearefull and carefull of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:20719:33"/>their children. <hi>Samuel</hi> was not in his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers keeping, but in the cuſtodie of the high Prieſt, much better ſure then in his mothers keeping: yet ſee how mothers nature workes; for though hee wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted neither meate nor clothes, <hi>yet ſhee makes him, and brings him euery yeere a little coat,</hi> 1. Sam. 2.19. leſt too much wind ſhould blow vpon him: and when the Shunamites ſonne was ſicke, ſhe <hi>ſet him on her knees till he died,</hi> 2. King. 4.20. but when <hi>Jeroboams</hi> ſon was ſicke, the Queene her ſelfe runs out to the Prophet for him, 1. King. 14.4. Againe, <hi>Salomon</hi> was his mothers <hi>Onely</hi> ſonne: not onely begotten, for ſhee had three ſonnes, beſide, 1. Chron. 3.5. but onely beloued: or if not the onely beloued, yet the onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued in that degree; for though ſhe loued them all well, yet ſhee wiſht and procured the kingdome to him; and when ſhe heard that <hi>Adonijah</hi> was vſurping it, ſhe ſteps in to <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. King. 1.</note> and makes ſure worke for him. And all this <hi>Jn her ſight,</hi> or <hi>before her. Tender and onely in her ſight:</hi> for <hi>Vbi amor, ibi oculus,</hi> Loue is euer looking, <hi>Samuels</hi> mother went
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:20719:33"/>vp euery yeere to Shiloh, 1. Sam. 2. Yea true, ſhee did ſo, but that was to offer ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, yea and withall to ſacrifice a little to her eyes, that is, to ſee <hi>Samuel</hi> too: for if the ſonne be but a little miſſing, or out of ſight, <hi>Siſeraes</hi> mother lookes, and <hi>lookes out at a window, and why tarrie the wheeles of his Chariots, and why is his Chariot ſo long a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming?</hi> Iud. 5. But if the ſon be dead or gone, <hi>A voice is heard in Ramah, Rachel weeping for her children, and will not bee comforted,</hi> Ier. 31. Now Lord that wee were but halfe ſo tender of our ſoules, as our mothers are of our bodies. But <hi>Salomons</hi> mother was ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of his ſoule too; for ſhe was a Prophet to teach him, for ſo is the chapter 31. ſtiled, <hi>The propheſie which his mother taught him.</hi> She tels him what a King ſhould doe, <hi>To iudge righteouſly, to iudge the afflicted and the poore:</hi> and ſhee tels him what a King ſhould not doe, <hi>Not giue his ſtrength to women, not giue himſelfe to wine:</hi> euen as <hi>Monica</hi> the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Auſtin, Toties parturiens filios, &amp;c.</hi> So oft as ſhe ſaw her ſon to do amiſſe, ſo oft ſhe was in pains of trauell with them. And thus
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:20719:34"/>to loue, is the <hi>tender, deare,</hi> and <hi>onely</hi> loue.</p>
            <p>But this appeareth better in the next part of the text. <hi>He taught me and ſaid vnto mee, &amp;c.</hi> Which followes out of the former, not (as oft in this booke of <hi>Prouerbs</hi>) after a looſe and independent manner, but it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes with a ſpeciall force, as if hee had ſaid, Though I was my fathers ſonne, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and deare vnto my mother, yet they did not coker mee, but <hi>taught me, and ſaid vnto me.</hi> There is a loue in parents, a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting loue which teacheth nothing; and there is a gouernment in parents which looſeneth all the raines, and ſuffereth to riot, and for biddeth nothing; and there is a pitie in parents, a fooliſh pitie, which par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doneth all, and puniſheth nothing, till God come with the ſword, as hee did to the ſons of <hi>Eli,</hi> and kill where the father leaues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrected: a ſtrange loue in parents, to kill their children with too much kindneſſe: but <hi>Salomons</hi> father loued him, &amp; to proue his loue, hee taught him, as thinking him much better vnborne then vntaught. If it be demanded heere, how <hi>Dauid</hi> taught his
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:20719:34"/>ſonne, the text it ſelfe ſheweth, that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time he ſpake vnto him himſelfe, <hi>He taught mee and ſaid vnto mee:</hi> hee taught him by word of mouth, <hi>as the Eagle teacheth her young to flie,</hi> Deut. 32.10.11. And as <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſaith, the Nightingale teacheth her young to ſing: and God knew that <hi>Abraham would teach his ſonnes,</hi> Geneſ.18. And carefull pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents are euer whetting the law vpon their children. Beſide, it is alſo like that <hi>Dauid</hi> taught him by an inſtructor, by <hi>Abiathar,</hi> by <hi>Zadok,</hi> by <hi>Nathan,</hi> or ſome other; and it is a chiefe prerogatiue of Kings, that they may chuſe their Tutors and inſtructours throughout their kingdomes. The father of the great <hi>Alexander</hi> profeſſed, that hee was not more glad, that hee had a ſon, then that he had ſuch a ſchoolemaſter, as <hi>Aristo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle,</hi> to teach him. And <hi>Alexander</hi> himſelfe confeſſed, that he had his naturall life from his father; but to liue well and vertuouſly, hee had it from his maſter And it is ſtrange to tell, what honour <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour gaue to <hi>Arſenius</hi> his ſonnes ſchoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter: And thus did <hi>Dauid</hi> teach.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:20719:35"/>
            <p>And conſider on the paſſiue part, that as none is ſo carefull to teach the ſonne, as the father, ſo hath none of the ſonnes ſo much neede of teaching, as he who ſuccec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in the kingdome of the father: <hi>Bee wiſe ye Kings</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid</hi>) <hi>and bee learnedye that be Judges of the earth,</hi> Pſalm. 2. It is true that Kings are Gods annointed, yet not annointed onely with oyle, but with ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all graces; but what grace before wiſdome and learning, which leades the way to all other grace, as Kings are leaders to all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men. <hi>Let the Lord appoint a man ouer the congregation, who may leade them out and in</hi> (ſaith <hi>Moſes</hi>) Numb. 27. But it was neuer intended by God, that they ſhould be blind and ignorant themſelues, who were <hi>appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as leaders</hi> and lights to other men. And what was <hi>Salomon</hi> admired for, but chiefly for his learning, and for his wiſdome? The Queene of <hi>Sheba</hi> came of purpoſe to heare and proue his wiſedome. And 1. King. 4.34. <hi>There came of all people to heare his wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome:</hi> as commonly when the people en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire after the King, they doe not liſten ſo
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:20719:35"/>much whether hee bee rich, for they thinke he may be too rich, as <hi>Julian</hi> the Emperor ſaid, that a couetous king was like the Splen in a mans body, which when it ſwelleth and groweth great, all the reſt of the members are in a conſumption by it. Nor doe they liſten ſo much if he be a man of warre; they like it well, that hee bee martially minded, and readie to encounter when the enemie giues cauſe; but they like it not, that hee haue <hi>Animum auerſum a pace<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> A minde ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting peace, or delighting in warre;<note place="margin">Pſal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8 30</note> yea cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are the people <hi>which delight in warre,</hi> ſaith <hi>Dauid</hi> himſelfe, euen one of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſouldiers that euer was in the world: but the chief thing enquired of the ſubiects is, if the King bee learned or wiſe, for then they know that he wil carrie himſelfe &amp; the ſtate well: in warre, in peace, in want, in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance, in all conditions ſafely and well.</p>
            <p>And that <hi>Salomon</hi> was thus wiſe, it was not only his fathers teaching, for men can but plant and water, but firſt he had helpes from nature, which had exceedingly fitted him: beſides, he was ſtudious and induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:20719:36"/>of himſelfe: for as it is Eccleſ. 1. <hi>Hee gaue his heart to ſearch out wiſedome:</hi> and which is more then all humane helps, when God appeared vnto him, &amp; gaue him leaue to aske what he would,<note place="margin">1. King. 3.</note> he asked not riches, long life, nor honour, but hee asked wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and God gaue it him in great abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance; for hee was ſeene in all wiſedome, yea he had <hi>conſidered all the workes that were done vnder the ſunne,</hi> Eccleſ. 1. euen as <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> the gouernour of Iſrael was ſeene in all he wiſedome of the Egyptians:<note place="margin">Act. 7.</note> He ſpake three thouſand Sentences or Prouerbs; his Ethikes or morall Philoſophy: hee wrote Songs, Pſalmes, or Poems; a Poet among other learning: He ſpake of trees &amp; plants euen from the Cedar to the Hyſop; his Phyſiques or naturall Phyloſophie; yea he ſpake euen of the beaſts and creeping things; A wonder to ſee a King come from his Throne, an Iuorie Throne, ouerlaid with gold, mounted vpon ſteps for Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, and euery ſtep with Lions on each ſide, a wonder (I ſay) to ſee a King to come from thence, to looke into the bowels &amp; vaines
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:20719:36"/>of a beaſt, yea of a vermine, the loweſt ſteps of naturall learning: what thought hee of learning which ſought it thus? And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are deceiued which thinke, lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to bee but a meere ornament to a King: It is true, there is facultie of orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as playing, ſinging, dancing; for as this learned <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>There is a time to dance,</hi> Eccleſ 3. and there is faculty of good vſe, as tilting, running, riding, promiſed to the Kings of <hi>Judah,</hi> Ierem. 22. <hi>If ye doe theſe things, ye ſhall ride vpon Chariots and horſes:</hi> but learning and wiſedome are eſſentiall to gouernment: he was no mere ſcholer, nor vulgar man, but hee was a King which ſaid it, that <hi>Rex illiteratus est aſinus corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Henry <hi>1.</hi> King of England.</note> that a King without learning was an aſſe with a Crowne; for to what end ſits he vpon the iudgement ſeate, which when hee comes there, may ſit, and ſee, and heare, but hath no wit to iudge? This <hi>Salomon</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſat in iudgement vpon the two har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots. 1. King. 3. and gaue ſuch a ſentence, as all the kingdome applauded to heare it: beſides, for knowledge of religion, he was
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:20719:37"/>
               <hi>Eccleſiastes,</hi> a profeſſed Preacher, as Eccl. 1. <hi>J the Preacher haue bin King ouer Jſrael, &amp;c.</hi> and that knowledge is alſo needfull for a King: for if a ſchiſme or ſchiſmaticall fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ariſe in the Church, hee is a kinde of perſecutor, that onely puniſheth him, it is more kinde and kingly, firſt, by learning to controll him. <hi>Constantine</hi> ſat oft himſelfe in iudgement, and gaue ſentence in cauſes Eccleſiaſtical, eſpecially in the faction and quarrels of the <hi>Donatiſts.</hi> And I could ſpeak of a King now vpon the ſtage, which ſpeaks, and diſputes, and writes, that Rome it ſelfe is enraged to reade it: for the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Clergie doe with their kings, as the late Queene mother of France did with <hi>Henry</hi> 3. her vnlucky ſonne; ſhee bids him play, and follow his pleaſure, and not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble himſelfe with the ſtirres in the Church, that ſhee and her <hi>Holy league</hi> in the meane time might ſet both Church &amp; kingdome on fire. In like manner doe they mufle their kings in blindneſſe, and ſuffer them not to looke into the cauſes of religion, that themſelues in the meane time might frame
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:20719:37"/>a religion to their owne luſt: But when God laid it vpon the King, that hee ſhould <hi>write himſelfe the copie of the Law in a booke, that it ſhould be with him, and that hee ſhould reade in it all the daies of his life,</hi> Deut 17.18.19. his meaning was ſure, that Kings ſhould bee vnderſtanding men, able to iudge and diſcerne of the law themſelues, and not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together to goe on truſt for their reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
            <p>It followeth in the text. <hi>Let thy heart holdfast my words, keepe my Commandements and thou ſhalt liue:</hi> whereby it appeares that <hi>Dauid</hi> did not onely teach his ſonne, but alſo catechiſe him, and teach him reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; for hee taught him <hi>to hold fast his words,</hi> and his words were the words <hi>of life.</hi> Iuſt as Deut. 8. <hi>the Commandements which if a man doe, he ſhall liue in them:</hi> and there is no learning but religion which brings eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life. And <hi>Dauid</hi> doth heere two things; firſt hee giueth his ſonne a charge, that hee doe thus and thus; and then if he doe theſe things, hee makes him a promiſe, that hee ſhall <hi>liue.</hi> Hee chargeth him moſt ſtrongly,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:20719:38"/>for firſt hee ſpeakes to his hear tor inward man, <hi>Let thy heart hold fast, &amp;c.</hi> and then he frameth his conuerſation or outward man, that he <hi>keepe his Commandements.</hi> The mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which he committeth to him is <hi>VVords,</hi> and words howſoeuer they are but winde in the eares of the ſcorners, yet <hi>the words of the wiſe are like goades and like nailes,</hi> Eccleſ. 12. like goades to pricke forward, and like nailes to hold faſt. And Chriſt ſaith, Ioh. 6. <hi>The words which J ſpeake are ſpirit and life.</hi> And Ioh. 12. <hi>The word which J haue ſpoken ſhall iudge you at the last.</hi> Againe hee is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, not to <hi>attaine</hi> them, for that he did by his fathers teaching, but when hee was taught to <hi>retaine, or hold them fast;</hi> and all this ſaid to his <hi>heart,</hi> Let thy <hi>heart</hi> hold faſt, &amp;c. For though it bee ſaid vniuerſally to all, <hi>Thou ſhalt loue the Lord thy God with all all thy heart,</hi> Deut. 6. yet it belongeth eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to Kings; and God vpon this very occaſion of annointing <hi>Dauid</hi> to the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ome, ſaid, <hi>The Lord reſpecteth the heart,</hi> 1. Sam. 16. So <hi>Dauids</hi> owne heart made him fit for a kingdome; and therefore now he
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:20719:38"/>calles for the heart of his ſonne, whom hee knew God had deſtinate to bee King. Let <hi>thy heart</hi> hold faſt, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now of an inſtructed heart there bee three teſtimonies: Firſt, ſincerity, that what a man ſee me to doe, hee doe it indeede and truly, againſt the faſhion of hypocrites: Secondly zeale, that what he doth, he do it feruently, againſt the faſhion of cold pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors: and thirdly perſeuerance, that what hee begin to doe, hee doe it to the end and conſtantly, againſt the cuſtome of backſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. The firſt thing is ſincerity, which ſtill drawes in the heart; as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid of ſeruants, <hi>Not with eye ſcruice, but as the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of Christ from the heart,</hi> Epheſ. 6. <hi>Dauid</hi> doth not teach his ſonne, as <hi>Machiauell</hi> taught Kings: <hi>Regi ante omnia optandum, vt pius videatur, etiamſino<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſit:</hi> that a king aboue all things muſt ſeeme religious, though indeed he be not: euen as <hi>Saul</hi> which ſet vp an altar, conſulted with the Prieſts, offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſacrifice, killed the enemies of God, and at euery word had God in his mouth, when all was but a flaſh: But <hi>Ablolon</hi> was
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:20719:39"/>more deuout then hee, for hee muſt goe to <hi>Hebron,</hi> and there pay his vowes, and offer peace offerings to God, for bringing him backe to Ieruſalem, and reconciling him to his father againe; a meere Machiauellian practiſe; for at the very ſame time he plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted how to winne the peoples hearts, and to depoſe his father<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2. Sam. 15. But <hi>Herod</hi> more deuout then hee: <hi>Goe, ſearch for the the babe, and when ye haue found him, bring mee word againe, that J alſo may come and worſhip him,</hi> Matth. 2.8. May come and worſhippe him, when hee went to deſtroy him: Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of mankinde: did <hi>Adoro</hi> ſignifie to kill; or <hi>Occido</hi> to worſhip? Is it not enough to murther, and doe miſchiefe, but to make religion the cloake? And thus did <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtata, though he hated the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and their religion deadly, yet he comes at times into their Churches, and falles downe on his knees, and praies deuoutly with them, but all for a further purpoſe. But as it neuer goes well with the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, where the gouernours are meere Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticians: ſo is it worſt with themſelues; for
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:20719:39"/>where God hath lift vp to the higheſt, hee looketh for the beſt, and if men ſerue him onely with a hood, where hee requires the heart, is not this to mocke God; but God is not mockt, witneſſe that <hi>Saul,</hi> and <hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, Herod,</hi> and <hi>Julian,</hi> whom we named be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Againe, the heart importeth a zeale to that we are taught, as Ierem. 20.9. <hi>His word was in my heart like a burning fire.</hi> And as a man cannot ſit ſtill which carries fire in his boſome, ſo hee which is inwardly taught, is inwardly toucht, and cannot keepe ſilence, nor cannot forbeare, but is driuen with a ſpirit, &amp; marcheth like <hi>Jehu</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Nimſhi, ſuriouſly:</hi> And it was ſpoken of that <hi>Jehu</hi> kingly,<note place="margin">2 King. 9.</note> if it had beene ſpoken perfectly, <hi>Come, ſee the zeale that J haue for the Lord of hosts,</hi> 2. King. 10. For he put downe the idolatrous king; hee killed his mother, hee killed his children, his kin dred, confederates, &amp; familiars; and when he had trained the Prieſts of <hi>Baal</hi> into the temple of <hi>Baal,</hi> he burnt vp temple, Prieſts, and Idoll, and made one bonefire of them all. Not like <hi>Rehoboam</hi> which ſuffered ſinne
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:20719:40"/>to grow, euen to the male ſtewes in <hi>Judah,</hi> 1. King. 14.24. and made the holy land like Sodom: Nor like King <hi>Ahab,</hi> which ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered the enemie of God to eſcape out of his hands, &amp; ſhewed him mercy, euen to his owne confuſion, 1. King. 20. <hi>Iudah</hi> the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tribe had his bleſſing from <hi>Jacob,</hi> to bee like a <hi>Lion,</hi> Gen. 49.9. Not like a ſheepe, to walke vp and downe in a warme fleece, and eate, and drinke, and ſleepe, and ſit, and ſee, and doe nothing; but like <hi>a Lion,</hi> and like <hi>a Lions whelpe,</hi> which carrieth fire in his hart, and a flame in his eyes, and a ſcepter in one hand, and a ſword in another, to forbid ſin, and to puniſh ſinne, and to puniſh it in the proudeſt: and he that doth not thus, hee is like the Church at Laodicea, Reuel. 3. <hi>Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hote, nor cold, and the Lord ſhall ſpew him out of his mouth.</hi> The third teſtimonie of the hart is Perſeuerance, to begin well, and to continue in it; for what a man doth from the heart, hee is neuer wearie of doing it, but goes on with Saint <hi>Paul, Through honor and diſhonour, through good report and ill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, &amp;c.</hi> Yea with Chriſt, through anguiſh
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:20719:40"/>of minde, and tortures of body, through ſpitting, whipping, ſcoffing, and ſaith not <hi>Conſummatumest,</hi> till <hi>hee bow his head, and giue vp the Ghost.</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid to al men, <hi>Jt is good to loue earnestly in a good thing,<note place="margin">Gal. 4.</note> but eſpecially ſhould ſuch a man as Nehemtah fly?</hi> Neh. 6.11. No ſaith King <hi>Dauid, J haue not ſwarued from thy law,</hi> Pſalm. 119. He had not yet; no nor euer meant to ſwarue hereafter, but <hi>J will praiſe the Lord, while J haue any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> Pſal. 146. It is no wonder to ſee the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall waxing &amp; waining of the Moone, nor yet the ebbes &amp; flowings of the ſea; but it is wonderful to ſee how men, made in the image of the vnchangeable God, yet change with the times, that where wee ſee the beſt beginnings and hope of goodnes, yet no man can tell what the end will bee. King <hi>Joaſh</hi> at ſeuen yeeres old <hi>did what was good in the ſight of the Lord:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. King. 12.</note> but at fourtie yeeres old, he did what was hateful to God and man. And it is ſaid of <hi>Nero,</hi> in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of his raigne, that hee was ſo ſoft and tender hearted, as when hee ſhould ſet his hand to ſigne billes and ſentences of
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:20719:41"/>death, he wiſht to God hee had not ſo much learning, as to write his name: but hee fell from that apace; for afterward hee killed men, as men kill dogs in a plague; hee kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led men for ſport, as children kill frogs and flies; yea he killed without cauſe or colour his familiar friends, his maſter, and his owne mother. But let this <hi>Salomon</hi> (whoſe heart is heere ſtirred vp to hold faſt) let him be to all men a fearefull patterne of Apoſtacy or back ſliding: but as himſelfe let ſlip what hee was commanded to hold, ſo God ſent him a foole to his ſonne, by whom he loſt, what he deſired to hold; the kingdome be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing brought from twelue tribes to two.</p>
            <p>Now the reaſons why men are thus weak in their retentiue faculties, that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not hold faſt, they are in the parable of the ſower reuealed to be three: for ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time the ſeede falles into ſtonie ground, where is no depth of earth, and how can the heart hold that faſt which takes no roote at the heart? Such a ſcholler was King <hi>Herod</hi> to <hi>John Baptist,</hi> who knew him to bee a holy man, referenced him, heard
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:20719:41"/>him, and did many things at his admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and yet killed him at the laſt; for his conſcience was but an vpper skin, his heart ſtill hardened vnderneath, whereby for lacke of moyſtening with the heauenly grace, all withered when the temptation came. Sometime the ſeede falles by the high way ſide, and that the foules pick vp, and thoſe foules are either idle and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring thoughts, ſtirred vp in the hart when the ſeed is a ſowing, or ill companions in mens cares, which doe more hurt in Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Courts, then the Caterpillers did in the land of Egypt: And ſuch were in the daies of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> which did all they could <hi>to make the King merry,</hi> Oſea. 7.3. and as if they feared his heart ſhould hold too faſt, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented him happily with vanity, and baw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie, and vnſauorie mirth, and made him to laugh when it was more fit to weepe: and ſuch were the young Councellors and companions of <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> gallants, &amp; whot ſpurs indeed, but men that had more ſpirit then wit, more fit to ride a horſe, then to to rule a kingdome, and the King by liſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:20719:42"/>to them, brought (cleane a croſſe to his owne account) his fathers loynes to a little finger. Somtimes againe the ſeed is choakt with thornes, which are expounded the tentations of riches and a voluptuous life; for as fire cannot burne in water, no more can the heart take hold of repentance, which wallowes in wealth and eaſe: and this was thought the cauſe why <hi>Salomons</hi> heart tooke no better hold, for hee had gold and ſiluer like ſtones, and all the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights of the ſons of men, Eccleſ. 2. <hi>Et ideò forſitan corruit</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bernard</hi>) whereupon many men haue doubted of his ſaluation; and therefore becauſe the harts of all men, eſpecially <hi>Corregis in manu dei,</hi> The heart of the King is in the hand of God, both Prince and people muſt pray deuoutly, that God would prepare and direct their hearts.</p>
            <p>But euery man hath a heart to goodnes; or if any man haue not, yet euery man thinkes hee hath this priuiledge, that none can challenge his heart, but God who is the ſearcher of hearts; and therefore to proue
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:20719:42"/>the affection of the heart, there is required the obedience of the outward man, <hi>Let thy heart hold fast my words,</hi> and then it follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>Keepe my Commandements, &amp;c.</hi> the ſame in effect with Saint <hi>James,</hi> Shew mee your heart <hi>by your workes,</hi> and with Chriſt, Iohn 14. <hi>Jf yee loue mee keepe my Commandements.</hi> Wherein <hi>Salomon</hi> is giuen thus much to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that though he was borne the ſon of a King, and by God himſelfe pointed out to a kingdome, yet hee is at command. And as <hi>Dauid</hi> who co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded him, was to him a father, a king, and a figure of Chriſt, ſo is hee heere commanded three waies: firſt as by a father, Keepe my Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and if ſo, the command of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bindes the ſonne ſtrongly: <hi>Honour thy father and mother</hi> ſaith the Law; but what honour without obedience? yea how ſhall hee keepe ſubiects in due obedience, who hath not firſt learned the obedience of a ſonne? It was a worthy ſaying of <hi>Decius</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Decius</hi> the Emperour, when his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet liuing would haue ſet the imperiall Crowne vpon his head; No (ſaich hee refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:20719:43"/>it) <hi>vereor ne ſi fiam Jmperator, dediſcam eſſe filius:</hi> He feared that it hee tooke vpon himſelfe the dignitie of an Emperour, hee ſhould ſoone forget the dutie of a ſonne: cleane contrary to the courſe of the world, for men commonly couet to take honour, but he thought it more honorable to giue honour, where it was by nature due. And what meaneth that <hi>Jch dien,</hi> the word or Impreaſe of the Engliſh Prince, but <hi>I ſerue,</hi> A Prince, and yet ſerues; yea &amp; he ſhakes vp his feathers, &amp; flouriſheth when he ſpeakes it, as if it were his glory as yet to ſerue. Againe, if <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpake this, <hi>Keepe my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements,</hi> in the perſon of a King, that command is ſo much heauier, as the power of a King exceedeth the authority of a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>Feare God and the king</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) Prou. 24. God and the King are yoaked in our feare together: yea and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired obedience to Kings, euen when Kings were enemies to religion, and ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from God. But if <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpake this in the perſon of Chriſt, or in the name of God, it is that which bindes heauen, and
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:20719:43"/>bindes earth, and bindes euen Kings as with cords, and Nobles as with linkes of iron; for as it is true, that <hi>Kings are Gods,</hi> ſo is it as true, that God is a King: <hi>The Lord raign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,</hi> Pſalm. 97. and <hi>Omne ſub regno grauiore regnum est:</hi> All kingdomes are but prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Kings but deputies to doe iuſtice for God; and without iuſtice, <hi>Quid ſunt reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na niſi magna latrocinia,</hi> ſaith <hi>Austin,</hi> when Kings ſhall doe what they liſt, and ſhake of their ſubiection to God; what are Kings but great theeues, as great theeues in their kind are ſaid to be little kings; yea and this is ſure, that the errours and irregularities of great men are extended and grow great by their greatneſſe: for, <hi>it is an abomination to Kings to commit wickedneſſe,</hi> Prou. 16. That which is but ſinne in another man is abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination in a King: and why ſo? firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Kings in ſinning abuſe the ſword of God, which was put into their hands to cut downe ſinne: ſecondly, becauſe they defile the very place, the ſeate of God, which is maintained by iuſtice, and ouerthrowne by ſin: and thirdly, becauſe their actions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:20719:44"/>for the moſt part exemplare, they ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the people of God, and doe more hurt by their ill example, then by their owne ſin. And be it true, that Kings heere may ſinne without impunity, as being ſubiect to no correction of man, but onely to the hand of God, yet they are ſubiect to God, and muſt account to him for the <hi>keeping of his Commandments,</hi> and muſt fall into his hands at laſt, where to fall (as the Apoſtle ſaith) <hi>it is a fearefull thing,</hi> Hebr. 10.31. And in the meane time they ſhall be ſure of this, that though they ſcape open outcry, yet here ſhall reſound from euery hill, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery wall a murmure of ill fame, which ſhal anſwere inſtantly, as Ecchoes to their euill, yet they know not whence. For though no man dare ſay, <hi>To a King, thou art wicked, or to Princes ye are vngodly,</hi> Iob 34. yet reeds will whiſper, and owles will crie in the night, and the ſonnes of darkeneſſe will raile, and write in corners, &amp; then what they thinke they haue done in ſecret (as <hi>Dauid</hi> is adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie) it ſhall bee painted like <hi>Belſhazzars</hi> deſtiny vpon the walles. And which is yet a
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:20719:44"/>more ſingular puniſhment vpon the faults of Kings and Princes, that whereas while they liue, they finde flatterers which ſooth them in their ſinne, and tell them they doe well, when they doe exceeding ill, yet when they are once dead and gone, then euery Chronicler, (which paſſeth ouer the faults of meaner men) yet when hee comes to write of Kings, he reporteth freely how one was prodigall, another was couetous, one was an adulterer, another a coward and baſely timorous; and writes it vp as bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as euery yeere Prognoſticators write the ecclipſes of the Sunne, and the Moone; ſo as where meaner men do oft amiſſe, and carrie it away in ſilence with them, yet their offences ſhall ſtand vpon record; that if a man would not forbeare to breake the Commandements of a conſcience to God, yet feare of perpetuall infamie ſhould bee a bridle to him.</p>
            <p>But what is the concluſion of all? <hi>Dauid</hi> concludeth with reward: Keepe my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, and thou ſhalt. <hi>liue.</hi> The grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt bleſſing which the father can giue, the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:20719:45"/>greateſt reward which the ſonne can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue? And indeed to what doe parents be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get their children, but to liue? to liue by v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of ſoule and body, which is by natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall generation, but chiefly to liue by vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſoule with God, which is by ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall regeneration: in which ſenſe S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid to the Corinthians, <hi>J haue begotten you in Christ:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.</note> and what doe parents for their children, if they doe not this? The life which is by nature, it is conceiued in ſinne, borne in ſinne, and proceedes in ſinne; <hi>and the reward of ſinne is death:</hi> ſo nature promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth life to her children, and performeth death: Is not this a mockery to mankinde? and are not naturall fathers meere mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to their children, if they bee no more then meerely naturall? But <hi>keepe my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, and thou ſhalt liue,</hi> ſaith the law; And <hi>this is life eternall, that they know thee, and him whom thou hast ſent, Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Ioh. 17.3. the life of the Goſpell; and thus is life propoſed to all: But to <hi>Dauid</hi> and to <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> that is, to the King, and to the Kings ſonne, it was a popular and peculiar accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:20719:45"/>as they paſſed by the ſtreets, <hi>Viuat Rex,</hi> God ſaue the King, or life bee to the King: Now vnder life which is the ground of all our good, the Iewes doe commonly wiſh and pray for all other happineſſe, health, and proſperity.</p>
            <p>And wee may heere firſt vnderſtand the life that is by nature; Keepe my Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, <hi>and liue:</hi> that is, liue heere: for though the naturall life bee not the height of our hope, yet the honour of a King de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth much vpon the preſent life, for while hee liues ſinne is puniſht, religion is promoted, Gods Church is built, and God himſelfe is glorified by him; but when hee hath ſerued his time, theſe ſeruices alſo are ended with him. Againe, while hee liues, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man praiſes him, and admires, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dores him; and hee is <hi>the light of Iſrael,</hi> and <hi>my Lord the King is as an Angell of God:</hi> but when he is once dead, his honour oft dies with him, and his light put out in darkenes, ſo Kings are Kings but for terme of life; that as this <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaid <hi>Jt is better to bee a liue dog, then a dead Lion,</hi> Eccleſ. 9.4.</p>
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:20719:46"/>
            <p>Or it may be that life is promiſed heere reſpectiuely, againſt hazard of death; not that <hi>Salomon</hi> ſhould not die, but that hee ſhould not die a violent death. Amongſt the Kings of Iſrael and ludah how many periſht, ſome by conſpiracie at home, and ſome by the ſword of the enemie? And S. <hi>Austin</hi> obſerueth, that of all the Romane Kings, two onely, that is, <hi>Numa Pompilius,</hi> and <hi>Ancus Martius,</hi> came to their graues in peace; yea Kings are maliced whether they doe well, or doe ill; if not for their vices, yet for their places, for enuie ſhoots alwaies at the faireſt marke; eſpecially where a quarrell growes for right of a kingdome, who knoweth not that ſuch tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als are made with hazard of life? But <hi>Thou thou ſhalt liue</hi> ſaith <hi>Dauid</hi> to <hi>Salomon,</hi> and <hi>Salomon</hi> found it true; for when <hi>Adonijah</hi> his elder brother roſe vp to vſurpe the kingdome, the vſurper ſoone miſcaried, but <hi>Salomon</hi> eſcaped, and raigned, <hi>and liued:</hi> and ſo ſhall it bee with all them which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend their authority, to maintaine the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God: They ſhall flouriſh but their
<pb facs="tcp:20719:46"/>enemies ſhall periſh: <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhall march through the ſea, as on the land, when <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi> and his hoſt ſhal ſinke to the bottome, as a ſtone: and as our eyes haue ſeene the great <hi>Armadoes,</hi> and inuincible fleets, part flying home with ſhame, and part or them drowned in the depth of the ſea, ſo let your heart hold faſt the words, &amp;c. and your Highneſſe <hi>ſhall liue,</hi> and feele the power of God in your preſeruation, when all Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiuellian, Italian, Spaniſh, and Popiſh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators ſhall fall before you in the field, or die by the ſword of iuſtice, and when they are dead, ſhall leaue nothing to hurt, but their heads vpon poles, and their rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten bones for reliques.</p>
            <p>Or it may be that <hi>Dauid</hi> in promiſing life to <hi>Salomon,</hi> did intend him life in his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, for men which are dead, yet are ſaid to liue in their poſterity; and when God was well pleaſed with the Kings of Iſrael, his promiſe was ſtil, that he would <hi>build them a ſure houſe,</hi> and that they ſhould not want a man to ſit vpon the throne; but when hee was offended with them, hee would <hi>bring e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:20719:47"/>vpon that houſe, and cut off euery one that made water againſt a wall; and he would ſweepe away the remnant as filth, and one ſhould die in the city, and another in the fields, and one the dogs ſhould eate, and another the fowles:</hi> And as it is ſaid of all the wicked in generall, that their names ſhall rot:<note place="margin">Iob 20.</note> ſo is it eſpecially the curſe of a tyrant, that he ſhal write him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the laſt of his name: as for example, In the degenerate kingdome of Iſrael, in a ſucceſſion of twentie Kings, the line ten times broken and interrupted; to ſhew that all tyrannie is of ſhort endurance. But thou <hi>ſhalt liue,</hi> ſaith <hi>Dauid</hi> to <hi>Salomon:</hi> and from <hi>Salomon</hi> to <hi>Jehoahaz,</hi> (which is ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome found in courſe of hiſtory) the ſonne for ſeuenteene generations ſtill ſucceeding the father: ſo immortall is not onely the righteous, but alſo his ſeede and propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Or it may bee that the life heere promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to <hi>Salomon</hi> was meant of a ſpirituall life, oppoſed to that, 1. Tim. 5.6. <hi>She that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth in pleaſure is dead:</hi> for a man may bee ſaid ſo long to liue, as he hath liued to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:20719:47"/>God: <hi>vixit dum vixit bene;</hi> but all the reſt of his life is a meere trance or image of death, as Epheſ. 5.14. <hi>Awake thou that ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pest, and ſtand vp from the dead:</hi> and when the prodigall child ranne riot and ſpent his fathers goods with harlots, <hi>Filius meus mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuus est,</hi> Luk. 15. the father pronounced, that <hi>his ſonne was dead,</hi> but eſpecially hee that ſhall riot in the gouernment, that ſhall ſuppreſſe religion, oppreſſe the innocent, and rage &amp; reuell in the kingdom, <hi>Mortuus est,</hi> he is dead to God, though otherwiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue in the world. And it is worthie obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that wheras all the Kings of Iſrael had both their ages &amp; yeeres of their raigne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded. <hi>Saul</hi> the firſt King, becauſe he ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned the kingdome with tyrannie and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety, had no ſuch computation made for for him; for God knoweth not the way of the wicked, but the ſhort raigne of the righteous is vpon record with God, and the one and thirtie of <hi>Joſiah</hi> is of longer account with him, then the fiue and fifty of <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> for of a good King it is ſaid, that his yeeres ſhall be as many ages. Pſal. 61.6.</p>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:20719:48"/>
            <p>And laſtly in this promiſe of life here is meant to <hi>Salomon</hi> the myſterie of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life:<note place="margin">1. King. 1.</note> as when <hi>Dauid</hi> was readie to die, <hi>Bathſheba</hi> bowed her ſelfe and ſaid, <hi>Let my Lord King Dauid liue for euer:</hi> Now the life which is for euer, muſt needs bee meant of eternall life; and this is indeed the very edge and point of <hi>Dauids</hi> promiſe: for what is this mortall life with all her pompe and pride, were it not a paſſage to immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall? yea and what is a kingdome heere, where all kingdomes were ſhowne in the twinckling of an eye, were there not in hope a better kingdome? a better king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome where all ſhall be Kings, and raigne with Chriſt eternally. And they which here haue raigned as Kings vpon the earth, ſhall looſe nothing, but gaine immeaſurably by the change: yea kings and Queenes when they come thither, ſhall caſt away their crownes, as <hi>Elias</hi> when hee went to heauen, let his cloake fall from him, and they ſhall repent nothing there, ſaue that they came no ſooner thither: and when they ſhall compare their earthly and their heauenly
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:20719:48"/>kingdomes together, they ſhall ſay, as S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid of the mount, <hi>Bonum est eſſe hic,</hi> It is good to bee in heauen, but for the earth, they ſhall be as loath to looke backe to it, as <hi>Moſes</hi> to goe backe into the land of Egypt; for their Palaces ſhall then ſeeme priſons, their golden chaines but golden fetters, their Crownes ſhall be but croſſes, and all their honours, but burdens and vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations: but when they ſhall looke into the face of God, they ſhall ſay to him with triumph, <hi>VVith thee is the well of life, in thy preſence is the fulneſſe of ioy, and at thy right hand are plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures for euermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FJNJS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
